hey hey hey everyone who EDA sorry for
my heart gee I live in a small town in
the North called Amsterdam you know and
today I want to talk to you about
progress pop-ups are we all developers
20% 30 40 yeah I think we're all
developers I'm gonna tell you a secret
and a little bit of a bad news when
we're building progressive web apps we
always forget about the users and for
some reason when you're building
progressive web apps it's always about
the technology but when we start talking
to users when you start showing them
native apps and progressive web apps
sometimes they can't tell the difference
if this is a native app or progressive
about but it's not because it's built in
react or view it's not because of web
components it's just because of the user
experience and the user interface and
also the real the reliability so today I
want to talk to you about progressive
web app from the user experience part
from the user interface part but I don't
want to talk about it I actually wanna
live code so let me put my screen and
you know the thing about live codes they
are quite dangerous especially with
pwace thank you we might need a new
domain
so because life codes are dangerous I
thought how can we make them even more
dangerous and I found an idea which is I
did not prepare for it I'm actually
gonna ask you for we're gonna do some
improv did anyone see the improv shows
sometime so an improv you basically ask
the audience for suggestions and you do
based on their suggestions so anyone
building a PWA yes what is that about if
you don't mind saying okay boring next
that's too matter if you do p.w about
pwace but I'll keep it in mind
other suggestions so technically an
improv you're supposed to take whatever
the audience says I'm violating it man
super exciting yeah okay anything else
no no I the thing is I want to combine
ideas that's it's not a no conference up
and digital dictionary all right how can
you combine all of these together any
more ideas so I like the unicycle one
okay we'll do something about unicycles
so based on my introduction I want to
tell you that a successful progressive
web app is not just about having scripts
like service worker and the web app
manifest but it's about when you meet
user expectations so I want to show you
this and I will actually take questions
while I do the live code so if you have
questions please go to slide odo just
another in the URL slash hashtag
questions and I'll have some of the
questions on my phone here if I forget
to take questions you can remind me
so we're gonna do something about
unicycle first these are the questions
so what we will have here is the setup
that I had I think you can't see
anything yet all right can you see my
screen yeah so we just have an
index.html SRC index of GS they're all
empty and we have a whopper
configuration it's pretty much very
basic and I'm gonna start with the index
and we need to just run webpack dev
server so we're on what pack dev server
and now we're up and running on
localhost 8080 and we're gonna start
building our app which is a do we do
people who unicycle have a different
weather no so we take the unicycle with
over other ideas someone said something
about tasks list yeah what was it okay
so we're fixing unicycle something so in
cycle return all right
I'm gonna start building this up and we
may use web components if we have time
later on but I'm gonna start with a
concept that you see a lot in native
apps and that's called the app shell
does anyone know what an app shell is so
10% the app shell is if you open any
native app like the Twitter app just
half a millisecond one millisecond
before you get the content you're gonna
have the app shell which is the
structure of the app without any content
without any data and this is something
users are used to a lot in native apps
because every single app has it on
Android and on iOS so even the camera
app if you open the camera up just the
split of a second before the camera
loads you're gonna have the app shop and
then the camera is just a blank black
three so let me show you what I mean by
that and let's start building our up
shell and I'm kind of doing server-side
rendering but just directly by inlining
the app shell because the absol is the
first thing you want to render on the
screen so I'm just gonna write the HTML
inside of here which may seem weird but
you're not writing everything just the
app shell so let's start with the header
Oh
first we'll need to add a script so we
can have a live reload this is gonna be
mind oh yes yeah now I have live reload
working let's start with the header and
then we will call it unicycle repair
then put that in each one and then we
basically have something that looks from
the 90s so let's go ahead and add some
inline stars I'm also in lining the
stars because you're giving full
priority to these HTML and CSS and
potentially JavaScript later on you want
the browser to render this first thing
so then we give this 90 just trying to
separate semantics from CSS and then we
say the header will have a certain
background color let's use a blue for
example and of course in my spare time I
memorize color numbers
and then we give it a color white oh but
I like to use CSS properties so let's
say this is gonna be the primary and
then we put it on the root the root is
basically the root of the document
most parent element I think and then we
need to remove the margin on the body
and then the h1 has a margin we can also
margin zero for fonts when building
progressive web apps you can if you
really care about performance and you
want to have something that looks like
native apps a lot of native apps use the
system font which is San Francisco on
iOS Roboto on Android etc you can now do
it as easy as system - UI a browser
support isn't great you can fall back to
all of this it's a lot yeah but it
basically tries every single font on
every on every operating system but
again you can replace all of this with
just system UI and I think browser
support for it is a 70% but if you wanna
have the best support keep it and then
start with system UI and now if I reload
the page and you inspect and go to the
rendered font it's an SF and s this is
San Francisco because I'm on a Mac if
you open the same website on an Android
it's gonna be Roboto and the nice thing
about it is you're not wasting resources
you're not getting anything from the
internet you could still use web fonts
this would only be for the app shell for
the system for everything that has to do
with the with your app but not the
content so I know it looks horrible but
give me some time we can also say that
the navbar will have a height of 60
pixels and then you can give that as a
height here and then we need to Center
things so display flex or grid there's
no I think place items Center but you
can do a line item center justify
contents
when it's all centered cool and now
technically this is an app shell maybe
we can also give a slight grave for for
the body but I want to take it a step
further and this step further is I like
to call it advanced app shell and this
is also something you see in native apps
which is a lot of the apps have a
navigation at the bottom it tabs
navigation does anyone know why it's at
the bottom yes I see a lot of this it's
because the thumb most people use the
app with their thumb so it's
conveniently positioned at the bottom
because you can easily navigate between
them so I want to do this
this tabs over here and I want to show
you hopefully you will learn a couple of
things from it because I think nowadays
is quite easy to make these tabs
if you focus a lot on the UX as well so
we can make it tabs and then those will
be links with a class top and inside of
it we will have a SVG icon so let's go
and find some icons from materials do
they have a unicycle like yeah
well yeah I don't think they have it's
like okay technically we're supposed to
get four different icons but I'm just
gonna use the same one to save up time
because we will have four pages at the
bottom so I'm gonna place this over here
I'm also in lining the SVG just for save
some time the P here and that's gonna be
tasks if we said we are repairing some
of the things and then I'm gonna
duplicate this a few more times because
we're gonna have several tabs okay and
this will be let's say help this will be
profiled and then stock we have the tabs
I know they look horrible we want to
position them at the bottom in a way
that they look like tops so let's go
ahead and make the tops give it a
display grid and then grid template
columns you can do one of our four times
or repeat for one of our and now let's
give it a background color of white oh
and position it at the bottom so fixed
bottom zero and now we need to give it a
left:0 right:0 it's getting there need
to remove the text decoration on the
link and basically place everything in
the center right and we still need ages
a long item center we have any questions
let's see what is it like to be a
Microsoft MVP let's talk after
oh I can tell you we get a free Visual
Studio code sorry I'll slide at those
slash hash tag questions so slide it
yeah it doesn't show here oh there are a
lot more questions I didn't see that
do we need web pack for this yes I am
using webpack it has a really small
configuration I wanted to do it with
parcel but I also want to use script
Idol and they don't support that yet
it's just a entry output but please
don't use this for production it's this
is horrible for production
what about user experience when it comes
to installing the app any
recommendations thank you we will
actually talk about this in a minute so
let me just figure out why this is not
working
let's give it also a height ABB's height
70 pixels so you might be wondering why
am i giving the height as a CSS
variables I want to show you that in a
minute
okay this P has a lot of margins
ooh I did forget something which is the
box-sizing border box that's one of the
annoying things when you start
completely from scratch so yeah no
difference but that's fine
it's planned okay this is our app so far
and then let's revert to color initial
and then one more thing on the on these
is by default we're going to give it an
opacity of 0.6 and only when the tab is
active then we give it an opacity of 1
and we can also transition this and now
we go down and only the first stop will
be active and now what we need to do
next is the screens so what will go
inside of it so let's go ahead and
create the main section which will have
the screens and then we will have a
screen x for let's say a B C D these are
the four screens that we're gonna have
and are you laughing at my code then
we're gonna put these screens next to
each other but every screen should be
full screen more or less so let's do
that with a screens
let's give it a height tough so what
would the height be here not a hundred
percent not a hundred VH so we will use
car with 100 V H minus the CSS variables
so the navbar height minus D bar tops
height and just so you see you may need
to close your eyes
yeah that's working you can only tell if
you do this like screw it up and then
yeah that's working now every screen has
to be full screen and inside of it so
this is where you can also do a display
grid and then grid template Collins
repeat for it's not gonna be one of our
but just show you what would it be
100 feet W and that's that's also
planned it's because you want to add the
overflow X scroll hopefully no it's
because the screen sorry
oh oh thank you
and now look look at it look how
beautiful it is you scroll you get to
the second page I know what you're
wondering what if you release mid yeah
it's it sucks how did I not think about
this how can we fix that so I was just
saying if somebody knows about this new
Web API and CSS property it's the over
it's the scrolls nav API so scrolls snap
type you're saying on the x-axis I want
to have scroll snapping which means if
you scroll and release it's gonna snap
to one of the pages so scroll snap type
on which acts and which axis X and it's
mandatory and then you have to say on
the children this no cause snap a line
will be start or Center there would be
no difference here because it's full
page and look at this let's enable
disable scroll release it's gonna snap
back to a scroll release it's gonna snap
back to
[Applause]
so
Wow very political question try to get
that at the end for these ones I would
recommend image to the ants like Claudia
nary so any suggestions for good tooling
to create for years all start up screen
images yeah I found it tool once for iOS
but I don't remember what it is sorry
but we can research it together if you
ask me later on all right
next what should we do next ok
so eventually this will be web
components hopefully we have time so
that's gonna be up tasks and then this
is gonna be up stock and then yeah same
for the rest and the next thing I want
to do is I want to tell the user hey
this is an app that you might need why
don't you add it to the home screen
but in a way that is not very annoying
we're not gonna have a pop-up nor a
toast it's gonna be quite smooth by
showing this I can over here so let's
copy it and then let's place it over
here give this an ID so Add to Home
screen a to HS and now it looks great
white and then position it on the right
so position:absolute right yeah it's
gonna be here but by default is gonna be
hidden so it's gonna be displaying on
only when we give it a class show then
we will show it to display block but
before we get to that you cannot ask the
user to install the app if you don't
have a service worker so we're gonna go
ahead and generate the service worker
and you need to install I am using word
workbook sorry web pack here so you need
to install the word box what pack
plug-in which I already installed to
avoid awkward internet issues so we just
require web pack work box
what PAC plugin yeah it exists and word
box is a library that helps you generate
serviceworker code so you can integrate
it with what park it becomes so much
easier and so we can read the plug-in
here which is work box plugin and we add
a new okay and under this object there's
the inject manifest plugin and it just
takes two options the source of the
service worker so you're gonna provide
it with a partial piece of service
worker it's gonna take it and it's gonna
generate a new one so that will be as
RCS wogs which we need to create and the
one it generates is swgs so we need to
create our SRC SW and we also need to
restart webpack okay and now we have to
import I was hoping you wouldn't notice
this we have to import the library from
city and this is changing in the next
version it it will be bundled in your
own repository but for now you have to
import it from CDN and what's annoying
is that you have to always manage the
versioning here and what you tell what
word box is simply you use the
pre-caching module and then you ask it
to free cash and route a certain
variable that will be dynamically
injected which is called Prakash
manifest so this variable will be
injected I will show you in a minute
this will be the list of the assets that
you have and this will instruct
workbooks to precache them when the
service worker gets installed so that if
we go offline the user can still get
access to the option so this is good for
now we need to register the service
worker so we can do that in index so if
exist a navigator just to make sure it
doesn't break on all older browsers and
then we give it the path of the Service
Worker this returns a promise so you can
dot then but I'm gonna assume that my
code is perfect and we don't need that
and now we have to go fullscreen let's
see yeah you start seeing these these
logs from work box they only run on
localhost and they tell you what's going
on you can also go to application you
will see a service worker is now
installed this one here as wjs this
shouldn't have been clicked and if you
go to the car storage we have the web
box work box Prakash there is Prakash in
this file now there's a bit of magic
let's go back and cancel and run NPM MPX
web pack and if you look at the distal
der we have this swgs let's take a look
at it colleges this yep and it's
basically the same as our code oh we
don't really need to import it it's
imported here so let's go back always
nice to figure this out during the live
code so let's run it again and in the
serviceworker code they import the
library for us and they import this file
which we'll take a look at in a minute
and this is the code we wrote and pay
attention to this self underscore
Prakash manifest because this is coming
from
Prakash manifest the father was
automatically generated by word box and
this basically contains your assets but
it also has a plus with it which is the
revision and this allows word perks to
be way more efficient than us writing
the code manually because it only
updates the assets that have changed and
can know if it changed based on the
revision so this is why a lot of people
recommend using a tool not writing
service circle yourself because it's
just very efficient to the cache if you
were to write it yourself you will have
to clear the cache add a new one every
time and it's gonna be slow from a
natural perspective also consume a lot
of data so let's go back to our backup
server and I also want to mention
something that in this life code we are
not going to handle the update of the
app so just like if you're on the store
you need to tell the user there's a new
version allow them to update so I have
to do it from dev tools this is of
course not for production and update
takes around 20 minutes so I cannot
cover it in the store but every time I
make a change to the server server it
will only update to the new one when you
click skip waiting of course for dev
tools you can click update on reload and
it's always showing in the fresher one
but this is only for development this is
not how we do it for end-users so now
let's get this checked and let's go to
the cache we have all of these files
cached which means now if we go offline
so go offline will it work
I hope so
it works so this is our app shell and it
still works offline why because even
though the network request fails it's
actually getting them from the cache and
this couch is APR this couch is actually
something you can access from the
windows hope you have this caches API so
if you know the name of the cache which
is work okay it's a lot can we copy it
works we can go to the console and then
cache is not open but this is going to
return a promise so you can wait and
then cash and then you can cache that
get if you get the index.html
at the match if is we're looking for all
oh yeah good point
it's the match sorry so gosh that much
and then index.html and it's going to
return a promise so wait it answers
response with the typo and you will get
a response the reason why I didn't get a
response is because I have to type all
of this but I'm gonna avoid it what I
was just showing you is that these
caches you can access them from the
window scope if necessary now let's go
to the next step and what we're gonna do
now is add the manifest if you want to
allow users to add your app to the home
screen you have to have an app manifest
and I already generated one before the
talk because I'm not gonna waste your
time writing all of this so what did we
call it in cycle repair and then you
have to give it the theme color the
icons I'm just using one of the icons
for my project so please don't use them
in your code
the background-color stand alone will
hide the browser UI and what is the
start here now you just need to link
this in the index as a rel manifest and
then manifest at JSON and you can test
that in dev tools which is very
convenient just go to the application
tab but we need to go online again
alright and you can see all of this here
these icons are just random icons and
now we're ready to ask the user to add
the app to the home screen so the way
you do that is by listening to an event
called yes someone who sing it if it was
correct before install prompt and this
gives you an event object do recommend
to prevent default on it because older
versions of Chrome were showing the mini
bar at the bottom which is annoying
especially if you have a top bar and
this doesn't show it but now this event
object you can call prompt on it
whenever you're ready so first what
we're gonna do is we're gonna say the
add to homescreen
element let's show it so we give it a
class show and then this add to
homescreen when the user clicks on it
what will we do we will call event dot
prompt and then this this is blocking
until the user says ok or cancel and
then you will have the user choice
promise which gives you the result and
this will be either dismissed or
accepted under result that outcome so we
can cancel out resulted outcome and what
I recommend for you is to always send
this to analytics because you want to
understand what kind of users what kind
of devices are accepting or rejecting
the prompt
will it work yeah so first this is only
showing up on browsers that support it
which is now I think Chrome edge and
Firefox but not sure which one is a dis
table or not this table but it only
shows up when the event fires and the
event will not fire if the user already
added the app to the home screen or if
it's the first second that the users on
your domain because it doesn't make
sense to add a website you just saw the
browser will wait a few seconds and
probably adjust your interaction so now
what you can do is you can click on it
and this is supposedly for mobile but it
also works on desktop if you look over
there
I'm gonna cancel it do it again okay
click it click on it and then you get
unicycle repeat repeat
yeah that was an accident as well you
install it and now you have an app
without dev tools of course and you have
it as an app over here and this theme
color is not because I have dark themes
because I specified it as 2 to 2 again
this is supposed to be for mobile I will
actually deploy this right now so you
can try it there'll be quite interesting
let's go back let's build for production
so MPX for park - P and deploy the dist
folder nice a worse domain name ever but
it's HTTP superficial flock if you want
to try this on your phone yeah it's this
domain make sure to have HTTPS a few
minutes HTTP this domain doesn't
redirect and you cannot get the
serviceworker to work so then you cannot
get the out to homescreen to work okay
let's get some questions
how much money can you ask for this app
you think how do you implement native
components such as sliders or motion
gestures such as a shake I think you
will need JavaScript for the shake I
don't know if we have access to the
accelerometer for it yeah that's a great
website where you can see also browser
support for it native components sliders
I think there is a slider component
input type range let's see
yeah you can use this one and it works
someone asked about Visual Studio
extensions they're not a lot it's just
prettier and peacock and lit and these
ones someone else a important question
which is how do you deal with is
dropping upstate when switching apps is
this still happening I think it was
fixed in the last iOS version the main
problem with the IRS now is that if you
have authentication and the user adds
the app to the home screen this app on
the home screen has a completely
different state than Safari so you're
not logged into Facebook you're not
logged into github in that case I
generally just don't recommend pushing
out to home screen for iOS users just
keep them in the browser and it works
fine and for Android you can do it and
that's what I'm personally using and it
works fine yes now we have more time to
do little element things so the reason
why I like to use little iment is just
because it's very very tiny ish so we're
gonna create a new files only 6
kilobytes gzipped so we'll create the
was the first page called app tasks and
then we will create this app tasks page
which extends from the lead element and
then you have a render function and then
we just say it works even though it
won't and then you need to register it
so custom elements that define and then
that's gonna be after tasks with the
definitional class of tasks and you need
to import this part so we import it here
and there is something I'd like to do in
most of my apps the modern ones this
script tag here which is at the bottom I
like to move it in the head which is
super scary because if you just make it
type equals module or if you make it a
Singh then it also acts like a preload
header at the same time you're telling
the browser about it but it also doesn't
block rendering so the browser can
continue with the HTML so it's just like
doing a script at the bottom and having
a preload at the top I know this is a
hundred percent correct for type equals
module I just cannot remember for async
can anyone confirm it is most likely yes
yeah in that case we'd have to use defer
to guarantee the order all right now
let's go back here and we need to serve
and it does not work Oh
because we are running on the older
version of the service worker so I
technically have to go here and then we
have out it ok so the reason why I
didn't work the first time is because I
was seeing the older version of the app
and I had to reload to see the new one
but this is the same thing with native
apps when you open a native app on your
phone it could be not the latest one you
would have to go to the store check if
there's a new one and update you can
kind of do the same with progressive web
apps but yeah unfortunately it's a
little bit outside of the scope for now
but what we want to do here is oh yeah I
still need to fix this because if you
click on the stalk it just reloads the
page so this is also part of the app
shop so then it has to go in the
index.html as inline JavaScript and that
may also sound look weird but you're
basically giving full priority to the
script and it's gonna be very minimal so
you say I'm gonna find all of the tabs
and then for every tab
is anyone using addeventlistener
nowadays
yes I keep hearing about react should
try it one day and then when you click
on the tab you will we will try to find
the previous tab that was active and
then we removed the active from it and
then we find the one that was clicked
and then we give it a last list of
active and finally even prevent default
now reload let's see if it works
click yeah this one is active and it's
not changing pages but there is
something really important when I talk
to you about this is not ok when we talk
about user experience see this empty gap
here this is super frustrating for users
so when building native like progressive
web apps you want to really focus on
these small details and then this should
be hundred percent there should be no
empty spots at the top or at the bottom
so I had a margin in there I think yeah
a padding through with a padding top we
can put it on the a element and it's a
really simple fix if it works but yeah
that's really important here and you
also want to give feedback that has been
clicked potentially a ripple effect but
I only have six more minutes so I don't
think we're gonna make it you can also
make it such that when you click on one
of these pages it Scrolls to the second
page of course but I'm gonna skip that
because you know how it works
and next I'm gonna create the second
element which is what was the second
element called app stock so we duplicate
this call it app stock
and this is gonna be I'm gonna assume
there's a method here that says like
activate or so something a custom method
that you want to call when this page has
rendered you can do it with first up
updated but I just want to show you
something that has to do with
performance and web components so I'm
just gonna say console the debug
activate was hold and go back to the
index import this to app stock reload
the page we're gonna have up stock it
works and the nice thing about our
components is that they are just HTML
elements with their own properties and
methods so if you find the app stock you
can call activate on it which is my own
custom method and that works great
activate was called until you decide you
start having a lot of components and you
want to lazy load them but thankfully
it's very easy you just import as a
function this is a browser feature you
can use it in all browsers but if you
have what park or parcel it takes care
of Polly filling it there may be one
browser missing it I'm missing from it
yet you just import it and then you can
have a promise when it actually loads
and it works but this is gonna break now
because at the moment this is running
app stock doesn't exist so you can do it
in multiple ways you can you can do it
with the dog down here I just want to
show you another method with custom
elements because other code grows
sometimes you don't have access to this
import and the right file what you can
do is you can use this window that
custom elements dot anyone guess it yes
yes
one defined and you give it the name of
the app stock and this is basically
returning a promise that will only
resolve when the browser has the
definition for app stock and then yeah
one defined then it's kind of safe to
call it I say it's kind of safe because
it may still not be in the Dom but here
I know that it's always gonna be in the
DOM and then reload and then activate
was called and I think what I did here
is the main page is the one the user is
gonna see immediately so I loaded this
as a normal import but this one it's a
secondary pager so then I lazy loaded it
because you want to give you want to
make this load as far this as fast as
possible and then lazy load all the
other pages oh that was technically oh
I'm gonna build and take some more
questions
I'm gonna build to a new domain just
easier for me flash it squirrel don't
forget the HTTP if you wanna try this
and
you please check in the project to
public repository yes I will do that and
I will tweet it afterwards so put it on
github then tweet it do you know why
people say and then I'll tweet it they
just want more followers I don't know
why they do that how to handle up
updates from the serviceworker cache is
everything I wish I can answer that in
one minute but it's really a bit more
complicated but what I did here is I
gave a full talk of about this topic not
as a life coach just a full talk so I do
recommend that you watch it if you're
interested in this and I also mention
the update quickly you can check out my
website and my Twitter what else
what about ie is that a serious question
well not serious because you can you can
still support ie with the script type
module let's let me show you quickly I
know it's not a serious question but
it's good to bring it up when you have a
script script async
sorry script type module this will only
run on modern browsers it will be
ignored by Internet Explorer so you can
ship modern JavaScript here and then for
all browsers you can have a script that
has a no module attribute which is on
purpose ignored by modern browsers and
then what you can do here you can do
main - legacy is and for this uShip
polyphase you you bubble or babel it and
then this works for JavaScript for CSS I
have no idea how you can make this play
grid work on ie and for the final
questions how does it compare to
automatic splash screens Android house
the question implies that they get
generated automatically by Android to be
honest I'm not aware of that are they
okay because if you try this up you will
have a splash screen as well
so let me see if I open like the Twitter
app so you have the splash screen and
then you have the app shell even on
native apps so it's basically doing the
same thing I think also for iOS but I'm
not a hundred percent sure oh yeah money
yeah okay and scroll stop support this
from IE 10 not bad yes but it has a
different syntax it's using an older
version that you can also use how
maintainable is PWA like this can use
dependency bots not sure what the
question is about but I guess I'll just
take the other questions afterwards
thank you very much for having me and