well I hope you've been having a good
conference so far and when I was asked
to speak here and I was going to speak
to their kind of main room and there's a
lot of you and I guess you all work in
different parts of the stack and I
thought what I would talk about is
really where we are as we head into the
last quarter 2018 as we look forward to
2019 where we are with CSS layout
because we've had some fairly big shifts
in that landscape over the last few
years
last year CSS was actually 20 years old
this makes me feel very old because I
remember when we didn't have CSS I am
someone who built websites with tables
for layout and I remember CSS coming
along and just for fonts and sort of
saying oh you know I'm not sure about
this not sure about this still so I've
kind of grown up with CSS and I've seen
what's happened you know how things have
progressed over time and at some point
you know we moved away from the whole
tables for layout thing and we started
doing stuff with CSS and doing scissors
fillet and all our websites got really
simple looking like our well this is the
web this is what the web looks like and
I think actually a lot of how we'd sew
things we say a web like actually stem
from a technical limitation the fact
that by using floats in absolute
positioning there's actually very
limited things that we can do and when
you look it at you what we've managed to
achieve by really hacking around with
floating things you know left and right
and making sure they're not too big and
that we don't end up with more than a
hundred percent because then all sorts
of weird things happen to our layout
everything that we've done so far on the
web to do layout has really been this
kind of series of hacks and for the
first time you know over the last couple
years with things like grids coming out
we've actually got what we could call a
true layout system for the web and that
makes a huge change to everything that
we're doing as when we think about this
system for layout I think most people
would probably think about things like
grid and flow
Xbox and that's really all based on top
of this idea of flow layout of normal
flow of the way that things just behave
by default we don't start doing any
layout and we've got things like
multiple column layout which I have to
mention because that's one of the specs
that I edit but that's a specification
that's there to do that kind of column
based layout so if there the big specs
they're the things that we would think
if someone said you know what is there
in CSS layout today you might think oh
well as CSS grid has a flexbox but those
things are held together by some other
specifications and they're really really
key to understanding the big specs that
we talked about we've got things like
writing modes which are really hard to
talk about and as you start thinking
about logical properties and values
we've got box alignment and we've got
CSS sizing intrinsic extrinsic sizing
which is really important now that we're
talking about layout that can kind of
work out its sizing itself you know
we're not taking control we're not
giving things a width and pushing them
around to make something that looks like
a grid we're actually letting the
browser kind of work out a lot of that
stuff for us so sizing becomes really
key and we also have these ways of
providing really great experiences to
our users whatever they're using to view
our websites because the web is kind of
exploded with all these different
devices you know I remember way back
when I started with the web and my first
computer had a 640 by 480 screen and
then I got a better screen that was you
know one or two four by seven six eight
and I felt marvelous you know it was
enormous and I couldn't wait for
everybody else to have as big a screen
as I had got you know what websites
could I create if I had all that screen
space to deal with and just as everyone
started to get these nice big screens
they also got phones and then suddenly
we were having to deal again with the
fact that some people had a very small
screen in front of them and now of
course we're getting webpage is
displayed on watches and it we can't
really sort of think well how are we
going to support
all of these different things we have to
develop in a way that is going to cope
with the fact that these exist and half
of them we don't really know what they
are and so we've got things like media
queries and then we've got feature
queries the ability to detect what says
CSS is available so these things are all
really important and then we can't
forget some of the other things that are
making their way into browsers we've got
CSS shapes taking us away from
everything looking like a little box got
transforms things like scroll snapping
and variable font and we're talking
about layout here but things like
variable fonts can have a huge impact on
our layouts you know been used
creatively and so in this talk I really
want to look at some of those
specifications that actually pull
together our big layout specs and you'll
see plenty of grid and flexbox code but
I think it's really important to look at
these things that pull these other specs
together because actually a lot of the
things that we think are confusing about
grid and flexbox for example and it's
sort of understood through things like
writing modes so let's have a look at
writing modes because it shouldn't
matter which way up your component is if
we've got a grid and we turn it on its
side like we're using a vertical writing
mode there's no reason why that grid
shouldn't behave in exactly the same way
you know tipped over on its side so
writing mode is actually a really good
place to begin an exploration of new
layout because even if you actually
never use a writing mode other than the
default understanding writing mode tells
you a lot about how grid and flexbox
actually work because these layout
methods have got writing mode support
bakes in because they've been developed
sort of since the point at which we
thought we'll hang on people actually
use vertical writing modes perhaps we
should have layout methods that cope
with that so a horizontal top to bottom
writing mode like English or Arabic you
know a left-to-right or right-to-left
language it doesn't matter which way the
text runs if it's horizontal then we
have an inline dimension which runs
horizontally the inline dimension that's
the way that your text
runs in the writing mode that you happen
to be using so if that's the in line
dimension then the block dimension is
the direction in which blocks layout
down the page in that writing mode so if
we take a vertical writing mode then the
in line dimension is running down the
page top to bottom so that because
that's the way that the sentence is flow
in that writing mode and the block
dimension is going to be running
horizontally
now you might use a writing mode to
typeset some text in that writing mode
but you could also use it creatively you
could it's quite common in in print to
see you know a headline running down the
side of the page or you can do that with
writing mode you can use writing modes
in a creative way and once you start to
work with those different writing modes
the fact that web design is essentially
tides the physical dimensions of our
screen starts to become a little bit
weird so I've got here a simple grid
layout now if I was to turn that into a
vertical writing mode what's going to
happen then is that the grid is kind of
gonna flip but the width that's applied
to it is going to remain relative to the
viewport it's not going to go with the
whole grid so what I can use is a
logical property a replacement for width
which is in line size so now the in line
size the size in the in line direction
is 500 pixels so the whole grid kind of
flips over on its side and it all kind
of remains relative to the flow
direction and that's what's really
important about these writing modes and
about logical properties is we've got
these mappings for things which are tied
to the physical dimensions of the screen
and tying them to make them kind of flow
relative there's a whole bunch of these
there's an entire spec full of them and
this spec is very readable because
essentially all it's doing is saying oh
well you know you've got these things
which are physical properties well here
is the equivalent as a logical property
it's all kind of coming into browsers
Firefox at the moment I think has the
support for logical properties and
values but they're being rolled out in
other browsers because once we're
dealing with different writing modes it
all just becomes very weird to be
dealing with width once you've tipped
something over on its side I've written
a bunch of stuff about this this article
has got a load of demos and things in
and the resources of this talk I'll give
you at the end a link to all of these
things but there's lots of demos you can
play around and if you use Firefox
they'll all work and you can see how
logical properties and values will work
but they're just mappings essentially
for things that we already have and in
reality you're gonna be using both
things because sometimes you do want
stuff tied to the dimensions of the
screen other times you want it to follow
the way the content is going so then we
have box alignment because once we
understand writing modes and realize
that our layouts are not pinned to the
top left of the screen then alignment
starts to make a lot more sense and the
thing with the alignment properties see
there's a bit of history there when we
first got flexbox we were all very
excited because suddenly we could
properly Center things both horizontally
and vertically here's like this spec it
appeared and that was the most important
thing about flexbox was the ability to
Center things we've been waiting a long
time for that it's fair so those
properties appeared in Flex box and what
happened was it's you know obvious so
they're actually gonna be more useful to
be used across other layout methods so
they've been removed from the flex box
spec and put into this box alignment
spec which means that we can use the
same alignment properties across any
layout methods and the one that really
comes to mind of course is grid layout
which is why if you know what about
flexbox
you start using grid and you're like oh
you know this is this is very similar a
lot of things work in the same way but
one of the things that people say
they're very confused about when they
look at the alignment properties in grid
and flexbox they say well when do I
align things and when do I justify them
we've got these sets of properties are
we aligning while we justifying which
access are we dealing with so we'll
start with grid
if you've ever found alignment confusing
and flexbox it is much easier to look at
grid first because with grid we always
have two axes and they kind of stay in
the same place so we can sort of work
out what the alignment does in grid
fairly easily so if your properties
begin with a line they work on the block
access it doesn't matter if your block
axis is like in English and is running
down the page or your block access is in
a vertical writing mode and so is
running across the page you align on the
block access and you justify therefore
on the inline axis now I remember that
because I think about text justification
if you're going to justify your text in
an editor then you'd be doing that along
the sentence that's the in line
direction so that's where we justify so
we can have a look at how that works in
grid so if we use a line self the
default is stretched so we get those
kind of full height columns if we align
self to start then on the block
Direction we go to the start to the
start edge there if we align self to the
end we're going to go to the end edge of
their axes and if we Center we get our
nice centering
so that's all on the block axis and so
then if we justify then we're dealing
with the inline axis so we justify self
Center and that other box goes right
into the middle and it's being centered
in that grid area that it's sat in and
if we justify self start then it goes to
the start now so then if we look at a
different writing mode if we go into a
writing mode vertical RL and I'm already
using in line size there so the box is
going to tip over you can see the
alignment properties work in exactly the
same way because we're still dealing
with the block and the inline access mam
really usefully if you're working with
grid layout you want to be using Firefox
and you want to use the good inspector
I'm inspecting my grid here and you can
see how all of the lines of the grid and
the tracks they're all apparent and you
can see them you can work out when
you're special needing alignment and
you're pushing things around inside that
box it's really handy to be able to see
what the grid area is
that you're aligning in and so
definitely even if you don't normally
use Firefox for development
you know chrome have gone down the lines
of giving us really great tools for
dealing with performance and so on
Firefox are putting a lot of work into
designer tools so things like the grid
inspector the CSS shapes editor or
really useful stuff if you're designing
for the web and you want to play around
in the browser so some other things you
might be working with and we have
languages which run right-to-left and
that affects things like grid layout and
alignment too if you're working in a
right to left language or for some
reason you've just changed the direction
which is pretty less likely and you're
then using you know justify items so
we've got just a fightin start if we're
working left to right the start is on
the left hand side if we change our
direction to right-to-left then start is
on the right hand side because it works
with the writing mode and the direction
of the text and flexbox is exactly the
same so then when we just fight items
end that actually goes to the left hand
side if we're in a right to left
language and to something else we might
want to align with grid and that's the
grid tracks themselves we tend to think
of grid layouts and we've got you know
the entire area is taken up by grid
tracks and they completely fill the grid
container but your tracks might not take
up all of the available space and in
that case you need to decide what to do
with the leftover space you've got some
grid tracks and then we've got a bit of
space left over here I've got some space
the grid tracks by default are aligned
to start in both the block and inline
dimension and we've got that bit of
space either side of them at the end of
the tracks and at the bottom of the
tracks there's a little bit of space
left over so we use a line content on
the block axis again to deal with that
space so if the tracks are moved to the
ends and the space is put at the
beginning the content properties are all
about space distribution and we can send
to them so when you're dealing with a
line content and justified
content what you're doing is you're
dealing with available space we've got
no available space nothing is actually
going to happen because there's nothing
to share out and so we get that sort of
proper centering of our tracks so if we
go to space between the tracks all kind
of blow apart and our gaps all get
bigger and if we look in the grid
inspector again you can see how those
tracks and the actual gaps in between
have spread out and also any items that
span over those tracks they also spread
out so this is something to be aware of
if you're spacing out tracks in grid
layout things are going to get bigger
than you expected and again you know
Firefox good inspector showing us what's
actually going on there and letting us
make decisions about our design so in
grid I think that those properties seem
fairly consistent you know once we
remember that we're working on the block
and the inline axis and which properties
are which it's fairly straightforward
flexbox is a little bit more complicated
because we can mess around with our flex
direction and so in Flex box it is much
easier to think about the main axis and
the cross axis and so the main axis is
the axis that you use when you set your
Flex direction if you say flex direction
row that's your main axis if you say
Flex Direction column that's your main
axis and a row will always be in the
inline direction in your writing mode so
a row in English is running horizontally
and a row in vertical writing mode is
going to be running up and down the page
on the cross axis we've got all three
properties we've got a line content if
we've got rapt flex items you've got a
line surfing the line items we'll have a
look at those on the main axis we've
only got justified content because in
Flex box were just stealing with space
distribution so if we look at Flex box
and we use justify content on the main
axis so here I'm working with a row and
I'm going to move all my items to the
end and the space goes before them and
if we do space between the space is
shared out in between the items and it's
nice and flexible
if we change the flex direction to
column I've got a height there so I've
got some extra space then it's working
exactly the same we were using justify
content in the direction of the Flex
direction and we've got this space and
we're spacing it out between and just as
with grid if we change our writing mode
it all just flips around and it all
behaves in exactly the same way because
we care about writing modes something to
note there's no so there's no justify
self or justify items in Flex box
because you're dealing with items as a
group on the main axis you're not
dealing with separate items in Flex box
but on the cross axis you can have
wrapped Flex items that wrap round and
if you have wrapped Flex items and
you've got some extra space then you've
got some space to distribute so on the
cross axis we can use the align content
property and it works exactly the same
as justify content if we've got some
spare space we can then use that
property to share out the space to move
the items around to Center them to give
them space between and once again it
behaves in exactly the same way if
you're working in a vertical writing
mode and so your columns are running
across the page now on the cross access
that's where you might want to align
your items against each other your Flex
container has a height of some sort
something is defining the height it
might be that as in this case the
tallest item is giving that liner height
or it could be that you've given the
Flex container a height itself so once
you've got a height you can then align
the items against each other so you can
align them to flex start so instead of
stretching to the height of the Flex
container they all hop up and go to the
start and if you line them to Flex end
as you can see we're working with a line
so we're working on the cross access and
dealing with our items if you change the
Flex direction to column then it works
in exactly the same way because our
cross access is now running across the
screen and so we can move our items
around on
it's access and this of course works in
exactly the same way we go there are
writing modes and we can switch it
around with writing modes and columns go
in the way that columns run in that
writing mode and it all works in the
same way so alignment is pretty neat
when I introduced the alignment spec I
said well the alignment properties were
taken out of the flexbox spec and they
were put into their own specs they could
be used by other layout methods now
they've got you know implementation in
grid so you can use those alignment
methods in grid layout they are also
specified for block layout and that
would mean that you could just have a
box inside another box and use the
alignment properties to Center it at the
moment there isn't any browser
implementation of that so if you have
you know one thing that you want to
Center inside another thing the best way
to do that at the moment is to turn the
outer into a Flex container and then you
can use the flex box properties to do
your proper vertical and horizontal
centering in the future we won't have to
make that step of also making the thing
a Flex container because we'll just be
able to do alignment on block layout and
but there's no real problem in making
containers flex containers it's just a
little bit weird that you have to do
that to make things Center at some point
in the future we'll get there we'll be
able to do that but so then we are
getting as part of box alignment in the
box alignment spec as well as all those
nice alignment properties getting moved
from flex box also the gap feature which
shows up in grids and in multi-core
that's also been moved into box
alignment so this idea of having gaps
gutters between items when the grid spec
first appeared it didn't have any idea
of gutters and this is something I
really pushed for that we should be able
to specify a gap between grid items
because that's a kind of normal thing
that you want to do in InDesign and so
we've now got a row gap column gap and
gap specified in the box alignment
property it box lament spec if you've
worked with grid layout you will know
that we have
weird gap grid row gap and grid column
gap kind of grid prefixed they've been
renamed as just column gap row gap and
gap but those pre fixed grid versions
will live forevermore as aliases because
they've been around already and people
have shipped things using them so you
don't need to worry about that it's kind
of for backwards compatibility reasons
we'll keep them but the nice thing about
those gap properties been part of box
alignment is that we will get them in
flex box now the only browser which has
started to implement the gap properties
for flex box is Firefox it's in Firefox
nightly at the moment I think it's going
into the next shipping release and
you'll then be able to do gaps between
your Flex items without having to do
monkey negative margins on the outside
and margins in between the items so
that's going to be really nice but it's
also a great example of how specs are
kind of evolving you know we're coming
up with some CSS in one specification
and then it's sort of making its way out
into other specs where it becomes
obvious that we need it that's kind of a
bit of process and things that are
happening and people ask me all the time
you know should I use grid or flexbox
and as you can see these things have so
many common features the answer really
is use both or either but use the one
that works best no one ever asks me
whether they should use font size or
color and it's kind of like that you
know use the layout method that works
we're not picking between bootstrap and
foundation here it's all just CSS so use
the use the method that works and the
best way to find out which method works
best for the components you're building
is just to build it you know build it
see oh actually this is really
2-dimensional so maybe it's not a Flex
component it's a grid component and it
doesn't matter what sort of component
you're building you can have grid
components that are tiny little things
if it's two-dimensional it's probably
grid if you just want something squishy
and flexible it's probably flexbox and
this cross over there but play around
because the more of this stuff that you
build the more buscar Vyas you look as
thing
design and say that's definitely grid or
that's definitely flexbox anomaly that
note sizing is another area where we've
gained this consistency between layout
methods but it really exposes the
difference in terms of how we've learned
to size things in the past because our
new layout methods are flexible we've
already seen how they distribute space
between items and they also can a
distribute space inside items so a lot
of demos out there for grid they give
you something like this and it looks
like the fr unit if you have three one
fr tracks you've got three equal width
tracks and that's not really quite what
you've got you've only got three equal
width tracks if you've got equal sized
items in those tracks if we put a very
long word that doesn't break into one of
our tracks then we don't have three
equal sized tracks at all and that's
because grid is sizing things based on
auto saying well what size is the thing
in this track and how much space have we
got left to distribute if you actually
want equal sized tracks then you're
going to need to use min Max and give
the minimum size zero so you're saying
this thing has no size and its maximum
is 1 fr and that will give you equal
sized tracks it may well cause overflows
and that's the thing about these new
layout methods they're trying not to
cause messy overflows they're trying to
take your content and display it in the
best way possible if you decide as the
web designer that you want to do
something different that's fine but by
default we're trying to display things
in a good way
and flexbox even more than that I think
flexbox really you know it's all about
I've got some stuff please just display
it in a reasonable manner don't overflow
it all over the place you know I don't
like poking out of the box and so if
your flex basis is Auto then growing
happens from auto the contents given a
size it's sort of its max content size
and then we work out you know whether we
need to take space away or add space to
let it fill the container and if you
don't want that you make your flex basis
zero if your flex basis is zero just
like in grid we're saying this thing has
got no size please share out all of the
space equally but flex box at heart is
kind of squishy and it's just for
putting the things into boxes and making
them sort of work out well and if you
are putting widths on all of your flex
items or specifying the Flex basis you
know as an absolute length to try and
make everything line up with something
else then it's quite likely that you
probably want grid which is that you
know that layout method that does line
things up with everything else I could
talk about sizing a lot to have entire
talk so I just talk about how big things
are and I've written up a lot of that
for Smashing Magazine
I think sizing is very very important to
understand to really use new layout well
and I think this sort of clever squishy
sizing of Flex books and grids it does
mean that we can get away with fewer
media queries it means that we can allow
grid and flexbox to squish and grow and
to distribute space inside the items to
distribute space in between the items
without having to add lots of
breakpoints but we can enhance that
layout with the use of major queries
quite often people seem to be very very
desperate not to use any media queries
and say no that they're still useful you
might not need as many you might not
need lots and lots of tiny breakpoints
but they can really help us enhance the
layout and and kind of accommodate all
of these different types of devices that
we have and we've actually got a new
media queries spec level for media
queries which brings us some new
functionality that we can use and we
have this idea of media features in the
older spec we should have had this idea
it's got a media types you kind of got
prints and and different kinds but
they're very very broad and actually you
don't really care what the thing is you
care what features it has because
there's quite a lot of crossover you
know people are viewing web pages on
essentially epub readers or on
televisions
or we've got laptops that have
touchscreens you know there are all
these different devices and they kind of
all cross over so it's a kind of bad
thing to be looking at well how big is
the screen oh it must be a touchscreen
because you know my laptop's got a
touchscreen it's not a phone so what
we're doing is we're saying we've got
these media features what features does
this environment have and one of those
media features which actually been
implemented in various browsers is to
detect the type of pointer the user has
because that's useful information has
someone got a fine pointer which is like
a mouse so you can click very accurately
on small things Oh have you got a coarse
pointer you're using your finger to
touch things and drag things around so
that's you know two different types of
ways of interacting with the content
that's a useful thing for us to be able
to detect you know have we got that
course pointer or a fine pointer so we
can work out how our user is interacting
with the application or site that we've
built and maybe change things perhaps
make the hit areas larger if we know
that someone is using a touchscreen and
along with media queries it's all very
well knowing that the user has a certain
type of device or how big that device is
or you know how they're interacting with
it that's a useful thing for us to know
but we also have this idea of well what
CSS has the user got you know if I do a
really fancy grid layout does the user
get that do they get something else we
never really know and we're never going
to know so what we need is a way for us
to ask the browser exactly what CSS it
supports and that's what feature queries
do they let us say hey web browser
do you support grid do you support
shapes do you support this fancy new CSS
that we haven't even thought of yet and
then if the browser does support it we
can use it and if it doesn't then the
fallback CSS will be used and they kind
of look like this they just look like a
media query except we're saying app
supports do you support and then
whatever you're looking for and propped
value.now which means that you can get
quite fine-grained if you know that you
know some feature of a specification
isn't supported you can just look for
that you could look for prefix things
you know the few that are still around
so you can find out whether the browser
supports something and then do something
because of that and that works really
well
because we've got really good support
now for feature queries everything all
the new browsers the browsers that you
are likely to come across that don't
support feature queries are your old
II's it doesn't really matter that old
ie doesn't support feature queries
because what you do is you use the way
that CSS works you write your old CSS
that works for any old browsers that
happen to come along any non supporting
browsers that show up then you have your
feature query and then inside there you
write your code that overwrites the kind
of old layout and adds all your fancy
new stuff that's kind of the way CSS
works and a browser that comes around
that doesn't understand feature queries
it's just gonna go I don't know what
that is and it can have it because
that's how CSS works it's this wonderful
language that just if a browser comes on
it doesn't understand some of CSS it
just totally ignores that stuff so you
can wrap up anything which might cause a
problem and for a browser that might get
bits of it but not say the grid code in
a feature query and sort of safely use
it anything new that comes along in CSS
from this point you can use a feature
query to detect support of and use it it
lets you sort of safely use things in
your CSS and try things out and enhance
your layouts for people who have support
for whatever comes along now this is a
useful article by Jen Simmons which
takes you through how to use feature
queries in exactly that way you know
layering on support for things that and
support in that case I think graders is
mostly what she's talking about because
the thing is you know we I think a lot
of us you know we're having to still
support old ie browsers and that's
probably the browsers that we all think
or you know I wish they would go away
but it's always been the case I remember
when Netscape 4 was the old browsers
that we all wished would go away and
then
I six was the old browser that we all
wished would go away you know this is
never going to change
although browsers are you know shipping
new releases faster than ever new CSS is
coming out faster than ever - and you're
never going to get a point where you
know new CSS features developed by the
CSS working group and overnight it
appears in everybody's browsers that's
just not going to happen
I mean increasingly we've got people you
know around the world who are using
mobile phones to access web content and
some of those are quite old they're
locked to older versions of browsers you
know we don't know what anyone's looking
at our sites with and we can't rely on
those fancy new features have been
available to them and so there's always
going to be browsers that don't support
something you want to use hopefully
those things will you know progress more
quickly most the time but it's always
gonna happen and you know here's a
feature that I'm sure fairly soon we're
going to be saying who you know this
this browser doesn't support this
feature and that's the subgrid feature
of CSS grid layout when we sort of
specified grid layout there was in the
level 1 spec this idea of sub grids and
the thing about sub grids you see with
grid layout and with flexbox it's only
the direct children of your grid
container that become grid items so if
we have a design like this this is the
sort of design that your designer brings
to you and they say look I've got these
three boxes and I want them you know on
them laid out like this yeah I go yep
and do that with grid layout that's a
really simple three column grid and put
the content in and it goes into the CMS
and then you end up with this because
the designer never gives you content
that like you know some of the headings
are taller and so on ask that's not what
you ever get it's always very neatly
lined up because it's got the same
amount of text and yet when things get
into the real world they don't line up
as neatly you have something about a
bigger font size or more content or
whatever is going on it's not going to
line up properly and that goes back to
the designer and they're like I wanted
those headings to line up
that's like go on off you go go and sort
it out and you can't because those cards
are all individual things while the
outer is all using grid layout in each
of the cards is it a nice column with
grid and we can make the internal as a
grid layout because we can make a grid
item a grid itself we still can't make
those things line up with each other
because they're independent they're
completely independent grids what we
actually want is to be able to say well
this three column grid thing has also
got three rows and the header of each
item goes into the first row and the
content goes into the next row and the
footer goes into the row after that
which means they can all line up with
each other now we can't do that at the
moment but sub grid which is in level
two will let us do that it will let us
say actually I would like this internal
card to use the grid that is defined on
the parent and that's going to be
incredibly powerful it will let us do
things like have you know a twelve
column grid system where things not only
the direct children sit on that grid but
things inside can also line up with the
same column tracks that's going to be
there for us to use of course it's
probably fairly unlikely it's all it's
going to appear in all browsers
immediately so again you know feature
queries will let us detect whether we've
got the sub grid value of grid template
columns and grid template rows and maybe
do something slightly different and if
we don't and you know the actually the
sub grid feature is kind of pretty much
finished in terms of the specification
so we're really just waiting now for
browsers to start implement it I really
hope that will happen soon so the thing
is all this is really positive I think
you know I'm very excited about all this
new layout stuff I hope you are too but
it does bring us new challenges we've
got all of this shiny new stuff and I
think we're only just learning how to
deal with some of the accessibility
implications that these new powers give
us flexbox and grid both allow for some
level of content reordering in flexbox
and in grid you can use the order
property to do
we reorder things in flexbox you can
change the Flex direction too you know
ro reverse or column reverse grids has
things like dense packing for auto
placement enough so you can then
position things on lines and so you
could very easily end up disconnecting
the visual display with the source as
someone for instance tabbing around the
document kind of ends up jumping all
over the place and that would be quite
unpleasant this is something that we
kind of need to figure out how we deal
with we don't really have a good answer
for that in CSS yet at you know I think
that at some point we're going to have
to work out how we can let a web design
to say I want the browser to follow the
visual layout and not follow the source
but at the moment anything tabbing
around anything reading out the content
is following the source and not the
visual display and it's really worth
remembering that a very simple test is
can you tab around can your keyboard
navigate around your site after you've
used grid if you can you're probably
okay but you know we've got new problems
new things to worry about and one of
these things came up fairly recently and
really this is a bug in browser
implementations we've got this very
interesting thing called display
contents interesting feature because it
lets us remove a box and visually from
the display so if for instance you've
got a bunch of list items they need to
have a ul and then you've got your
allies if you had a pair and sort of
grid structure going on you just wanted
those list items to sit on the grid you
can use display contents to visually
remove the UL and then leave the items
but semantically the UL should still be
there and anyone coming to the site you
know using a screen reader should know
that that's a list so this is really
kind of how this works I've got a grid
here as we know direct children
participate in grid layout the children
of those items do not adding display
content to the grid item removes the box
of that item and anything about the Box
the width the borders anything like that
and the children can then participate in
grid layout that's really neat as I say
semantically it should still remain
whatever the element was in the
first place there is a book in all the
browsers that have implemented that mean
that actually semantically doesn't mean
that they're also saying oh well you've
removed that list you've removed that
table structure and therefore you are
now no longer a list or table that is a
bug the spec says they shouldn't do it
but they do it's getting fixed this post
is a really good run down of what
display contents is and the potential
problems with it but the thing here
really is just that we've got this new
stuff and there are going to be new
things that pop up and you might be the
first person to encounter one of them
because this stuff is so new and some of
these problems might show up only in
combination with other bits of CSS and
so you know do be looking out for stuff
and testing if you're using new stuff
you know don't be so sure that people
won't have introduced bugs like this you
know when it was first mentioned to me I
was like what but the spec doesn't say
that but you know books happen and so
we've got this yeah amazing new system
for layout you know I'm it really is so
fantastic how far things have come in
the last few years and we're not
stopping here to say you know we've got
sub-grid coming along we're not stopping
here and when you hit the edges when
you're working with this stuff and
you're like hang on why can't we do
whatever then let us know because so
much of what I've shown you today just
comes from filling in the needs of
people who've said why can't we do
whatever well because no one specified
that yet no one's implemented it no
one's come up with it so as we're using
this new stuff you know when you find
the places where there are things that
we can't yet do let us know and this is
how you let the CSS working group know
these are the issues on CSS specs now
some of those look baffling even to me
and I'm part of the CSS working group
but a lot of them are very
straightforward things that people are
asking for and showing examples and in
fact actually the more you can describe
the use case the thing that you can't do
the better because it turns out that
developing CSS
much like developing any product now if
someone uses your product and they come
along with a really good use case and
say you know I need to do this thing and
I can't do it because and I'm working
round it by doing this then often it's
really easy as a product developer to
say oh yeah we could add that I could
fix that for you and it's the same for
CSS if someone comes along and says look
this is something we can't do and we're
having to do it with JavaScript and it
makes it a bit slow and janky it'd be
great if we have CSS way to do it that's
actually something that may well get
picked up and specified and implemented
and because you know things are
happening so much more quickly you know
it's not going to happen for a product
the project you need to work on tomorrow
but it might be around you know next
year you know do yourself a favor for
your future self as it were and sort of
talk to people and explain the things
that you can't do because when we look
at browsers now you know look at what's
going in these the last releases of a
few browsers Firefox 62 CSS shapes and
the shape path editor variable fonts
chrome 69 scroll snapping display
cutouts for your notches and connect
gradients an edge had variable fonts you
know every time a browser release ships
there is a whole bunch of new stuff
isn't it it's a really really exciting
time to be a web developer you know I've
been doing this for 20 years but it's
why I'm still excited about it you know
why I haven't gone off to do something
else and why I still want to participate
and keep making it better and I really
hope that you are all excited about it
too and all of my code examples and the
slides and so on and some resources are
at that URL thank you for listening
enjoy the rest of the conference