[Music]
thank you very much Joe it's working can
you hear me
perfect great okay so first of all thank
you for choosing this session over the
other it's a pleasure having you here
today I'm very excited to be on the
stage today because it's the first time
I'm delivering this talk and to be
honest it's also very challenging
because I'm trying to summarize in two
years of work in 30 minutes that is
really really interesting so today I
want to introduce you on my vision of a
micro from x architecture it's not a new
topic but there are many approaches that
we can have I would like to give you
mine as joe said my name is Luca I'm
chief architect at the zone the zone a
is an OTT platform it's available in
seven countries we are already we
already have hundreds of developers we
have millions of customers is a really
interesting challenge because we have 30
devices that we have to keep on track
and deliver our applications we have a
delivery video delivery pipeline is very
complex that's basically the Netflix
source port I'm a Google developer
expert on web technologies and I'm
organizing in London a lot of meetups
with my community so if you are in
London and you're looking for a meet-up
but usually we organize one per per
month so feel free to join us so what we
are going to cover today so first of all
we will do a journey from a monolith to
micro anything and then we were talking
about what is a microphone 10 we will
define some principles around them and
we will end oh and we will end up with
some technical implementation or let's
say different option that we can have in
order to embrace this new architecture
first of all and foremost obviously this
one is as I said the first time that I
do this talk but in order to arrive to
these ideas and and concept I had to be
very open mind and questioning all the
best software developer practices that I
studied in the past so please be
open-minded during this talk and think
at scale because this is one of the way
that you will embrace better
the DS architecture okay so I joined the
zone four years ago we started we are
still a startup in a certain way despite
the number of people that are working on
the zone and I remember the one of by
the first day that was there and the CPU
came to my desk said listen look up I
know that you are the second tech person
that was hired inside this company but
at the same time I would like that you
think broadly and you start to think at
scale because what we would like to have
in the zone is having undress of
developers that are working on the same
platform and the same codebase and to be
honest in a certain way as an architect
I was a bit scared because if you think
about that you know you are the second
that joined the company as a tech person
and suddenly you discover that you
already have to this huge challenge to
think about an architecture that could
empower developers both distributed
teams across the world working on the
same code base so it is a big challenge
so beard that in mind let's start to
this journey that was basically the
journey that I did in order to move
forward towards the micro world as I
call it so when we start the usually
when you start a new project or if you
work in a startup usually what what you
really care about at the beginning is
retrieving quickly a feedback from from
your potential customers right so the
tech stock is important but not
essential what we usually what you do is
you tend to obviously the time to market
is more important therefore you - you
tend to maybe cut some corners but
usually 90% of the time what you hand up
having is I say a database that is
shared across multiple api's you have an
NPI layer that is storing what they call
a monolith that basically contains all
your API is integration with third-party
companies and so on and then on the
client side you have a single page
application single page application a
peak that that architecture just because
obviously there are several several
others that you can pick it could be
server-side rendered you can have single
pages but single page application is one
of the most used where you download that
the entire code base and basically then
you just consume sub you API is in order
to view the rendering rendering the view
and and then when when you validate your
ideas and the company starts to grow you
identify what are the areas that has to
grow with the company and the
organization so what you start to do is
taking your monolith breaking it up in
multiple micro-services you start to
have one database for microservices
because otherwise it's an anti-pattern
using a shared database for a multiple
micro service you have your
infrastructure that is dedicated for
that and then you start to divide your
teams following and they say the way how
the business works but what what do you
do on the client side on the client
usually what you have is a I don't know
tens of developers that are working on
the same codebase how they started and
it's becoming more difficult every time
every iteration because if they're not
very prescriptive in the way that they
are working you need to have let's say a
code base that is exploding and it's way
more difficult if you start to have
distributed teams because we distributed
teams is very very hard part from Puglia
having two requests that you can check
what is the outcome of you of your
codebase
so the import with your team so usually
on the front hand side we as we said we
have a unique code base that is managed
by multiple teams what we need to manage
a lot is the communication overhead
between different parts of the
organization and particularly if you
have if you have a distributed team on
instead if you check what is happening
on the infrastructure side so the
website and and back inside they start
to have a structure that allowed them to
scale independently some part do I have
they have some strong boundaries around
what they are delivering and everything
became easier in a certain way because
if they design properly they're
microservice in the api's they just
define a contract and they stick with
that and then they are completely
autonomous to deliver a new micro
service a new version they can there are
some a lot of engineering engineering
practices that you can use in order to
ensure that your micro service is not
breaking up the entire platform also in
production so a lot of these things but
on the client side it wasn't exactly the
same things right so as we said this is
our situation and I would like to - that
you stick that in mind because this is
how often these kind of things are
working
but what if we change this thing what if
we start to take the principles of
microservices and apply to the client
side what if we start to say okay so
domain driven design is not only for for
the back end it could be applied those
on the front end at the end of the day
if you think about that we have a
monolid we break it apart and we start
to have multiple api's that are managed
by multiple containers or I don't know
lambdas or whatever you prefer to deal
with and then you start to have let's
say an infrastructure that is dedicated
for certain micro service and you can
have votes on the front end you can
break apart the SP a monolith I have
English saved some challenges obviously
because obviously you need to find a way
to work it straight which client which a
microbe microphone tank you won't load
but at the end of the day you can do
that and you can end up on something
under an architecture like that
obviously is a simplification but why
not so if we if we let's say start to
begin a little bit further with that we
can start to see something very
interesting so first of all the impact
to the team because we don't think often
as architects or too much on the process
of how we structure the team but we have
to do that because if we want to scale
your company that is probably one of the
most important thing in particular for
the front-end front-end if you scale the
front and you don't have to scale
infrastructure because we are delivering
vast majority of the time static files
so CD s are doing that for us what we
need to scale and think about that is it
are the teams because that is the
complicated part but it with micro front
ends we can start to introduce a way to
speed up the throughput of our teams
because we can have cross-functional
teams that are managing the Microsoft
API layer the infrastructure layer and
the front-end layer in our in autonomy
they don't have to let's say communicate
with other teams as long the contracts
are respected they start to have freedom
responsibility because they own the
force at hand - and for the first time
they they can innovate as we know one of
the best one of the pleasure working
with micro services is the fact that you
can have multiple technology stock on
when you are designing your Europe eyes
we can do the same on micro front ends
why you can have you cannot have like
the no part of your application written
in beauty yes in part with react and
redux and part with angular it's totally
feasible so let's talk about what is a
micro friend from front end now so this
is my definition obviously you cannot
find much on on the web so I'm working
hard in order to provide some
information so starting from a DD
perspective micro front ends are a
technical representation of a business
domain subdomain and they provide strong
boundaries with clear contracts and they
avoid sharing logic with other
subdomains that for me is a let's say
and a definition that is providing
clarity on what we are trying to achieve
with microphone tents and I would like
to check the key part of this sentence
so representation of business subdomain
with strong boundaries and clear
contracts and avoid sharing logic so
domain a subdomain is not a new concept
is something that is applied in domain
driven design for a while and often
domain driven design is is thought
mainly for for back-end layers but we
should do users on the front end so
let's see what what is a domain a domain
is the problem to be addressed with the
software effort so if you think about
Netflix I hope that everyone knows what
Netflix is the domain for them is an OTT
platform that is trying to deliver
movies with streaming okay but obviously
if you we take all this domain or
together is very complex because there
are a lot of things inside there that we
have to think about subscription came
and catalog and so on and therefore we
did it is tending to say okay so if we
have a domain you can split it up in
multiple subdomains and usually if you
do that very well and you master the
domain you can start to map your
subdomains also with teams and that is
very important because obviously you can
start to have light another payment team
and you have like the infrastructure
team and your front and the back end
team and the cross-functional team
working together with the product and
that is something very very important
because when you have that it means that
the communication where I'd start to
diminish a lot another key concept of
micro front ends for me is
share nothing and I know that it's very
painful at the beginning because the
first thing that we tend to do on the
front end is okay so I have to create my
application there are some components
that are available in multiple area of
my application let's create a component
library and trust me I spend a lot of
time working with on this topic with
developers and they know what are the
pros and cons of this I know that there
is a lot of resistance at the beginning
but the fact that you are so if you
think about the microservice usually
with the macro service you you share
really a little bit that usually are
logs and monitoring and often are not
even inside your code what if we can do
the same on on the front end honestly
what we have done so one of the things
that usually we have in the zone a lot
of people are saying okay we have
multiple microphone tents and we have
the header and footer that are
replicated I don't know five six times
copy and paste and then changed and a
lot of people are saying oh yes but that
that is a bad practice because we are
copying code and every time we need to
change we need to change five times but
the question is how often the header and
footer is changing during the lifecycle
of a platform so I checked that that
thing and we changed twice in three
years so is it really a problem the fact
that we are adding a new label inside
the header or we are changing the color
of the font I don't think so I think
that the throughput is way more
important and then thinking on okay we
have to to deal with this duplication of
code and if it's well address is not a
big deal so how we can approach
microphone tents because there are
several ways that to do that it's not as
I said it's not a new concept but we are
trying to find the right way to do that
so for instance modify in the desktop
application they they work with iframes
it's a massive application that is based
on web technologies for the UI and the
C++ behind the scene and what they are
doing basically are creating multiple
iframes that are their minor front ends
and inside the view there is I don't
know the microphone time for it for the
music player they ever I don't know what
your friends are listening there is the
least catalogue microphone Tennison and
they communicating together via an even
that is injecting inside microphone tan
that is one option obviously the
question here is how we can let's say
assemble these views in a proper way
probably there is another team that is
doing that probably the reserves
responsibility of a specific team but
still there is a lot of communication at
this going on open table another large
organization they have distributed teams
in Australia London and San Francisco
Furman well they created after so they
started this journey of microphone tans
in 2014 if I remember well and they they
basically created a developer experience
team that the delivered is open
components as an open source project
where basically when we define a
component is a front-end back-end
and style and everything server-side
render the component that the store
inside the registry think about doctor
if you're familiar with that and each
single team can pick up from this
registry the components that they want
and they compose the application without
much communication at the end because if
there is a team in Australia that is
creating I don't know header then it
could be used anywhere else obviously
there is some coordination that has to
happen on this side that cross region
but at the end is really an interesting
and interesting approach
that is another another approach for
microphone tans as well obviously for
smooth for making a smoother the
experience for developers they created
also CLI but that means at the same time
that a new joiner in in open table has
to learn all these things and start to
use all the tools that are available
inside the company the first example
that is the one that is closer to my my
ideas is the landed these fashioning
comers and several several years ago I
attempt to talk made by one of their
engineers and the interesting bit there
is that they basically created an
open-source framework or mosaic and
there there is a specific part called
Terry Taylor Jes and what Taylor does is
basically created at runtime that your
pages basically there is a tiny layer
that every time you request a page they
are assembled
HTML fragments on the go obviously they
are highly cacheable because when you
have like I don't know tracksuit from
adidas it would be always that you don't
have to serve something specific but in
that case they can do that they can work
at scale they produce these pages they
cash on and CDN and that that's it the
tailor is written in in go it was one of
the first experiments that they so
pretty brilliant for forefront and
written in gold they were inspired by a
big pie from Facebook so you can see a
big Python on Facebook pages it's more
or less similar but to so in this case
we are talking about components that are
assembled at runtime on the server we
took a different approach in this case
because one thing that I was thinking
when when I was designing this
architecture is okay so now we have like
one or a small team of developers start
working on one platform that is web but
we need to target 30 platforms we need
also to have a distributed distributed
teams that are sharing the same codebase
because they have to work on same
codebase and who else who knows what
could happen next so the first thing
that I did I take our application that
if you think about Netflix is very
similar and I I work with the domains so
I started to slice and dice my my
application in multiple domains
subdomains so we have the landing page
subdomain we have the authentication
that contains sign in/sign up retrieve
email every pass for payment altogether
we have discover in playback where we
have basically the core of the zone
where we have the catalog we have a
search functionality we have a scheduled
functionality and we have the playback
then we have the customer support where
we have the help and the chart the
contact hours and so on and we have my
account where you can basically change a
few of the things so those are the let's
say the key domains that we have
subdomains that we have inside the zone
domain and those are mapped one to one
with our product team so we have a
product team that is managing payment we
have a product is managing I don't know
the acquisition we have a prior protein
for managing the landing page sometimes
the product team is composed by one
person only some
I'm gonna say compost more people
discover in playback is pretty huge for
instance but this is how we restructure
things and each single of these areas
are represented in technically speaking
with a single page application so each
of them is a single single page
application some of them they are not
even sharing the same stuff technology
stuff some of them are based on react
demo backs some other just react we are
doing some tests with other technologies
but all of them are completely different
projects managed by different tips and
they know that work is straightest
because that the complexity of this is
not creating multiple single page
applications is how we deliver to the
client and I spend a lot of time
thinking about that and at the end what
they came up from in order to avoid
scalability issues because the problem
that we have compared to the Rando is we
need to create something that is highly
scalable that is completely customized
for for the user therefore we cannot use
too much the CDN right now for serving
our content because there are too many
permutation so I created this layer this
called the bootstrap and is the first
thing that is downloaded when you type
[Music]
www.hp.com the applique user is watching
the zone and and retrieving the
configuration for that specific country
then is obstructing the input-output
operation for all the other single page
application or microphone tents because
one of the problems you have when you
work on on TVs in particular is that the
API for writing something on on the
Bradys is there completely different
between manufacturer or in the same
manufacturer between different Smart TVs
editions so if you have a Samsung course
I and Samsung Tizen there are completely
different API is to write that so
therefore if if each single microphone
tenders should know this kind of
permutation it means that we need to
create one for each single platform but
honestly we can abstract that and the
bootstrap is doing this the other thing
is the doing the routing between
microphone tans so he understands in
which which state is in which state the
user
and then based on that is retrieving
them the right microphone tense so you
understand if the user is signed in and
if it's signed in it will go straight to
the delivering playback if it's not
signed in it will really start of serve
the landing page unless there is a deep
link and that case is going to the
authentication page for instance the
last thing is it's sharing configuration
across multiple microphone test so in
that case because it's a vanilla just
layer that is just exposing some stuff
we are just exposing things that are
happening in in one area in one
microphone tense and making available
for other microphones and to listen to
that also for instance I don't know
marketing pixel or analytics like Google
tag manager stuff like that are living
inside the bootstrap and the bootstrap
is the key of our of our strategy
because obviously if you think about
that we need to deliver around 20 Smart
TVs application and if I start to have
like the less a specific code the
domain-specific code inside each single
microphone 10 therefore if it's
impossible for us because we need to
have so much effort in order to make it
right
that is very difficult we said if I
obstruct that on the bootstrap is very
interesting because it became very
natural I can reuse authentication
everywhere without changing anything
the other interesting thing of this is
that we can do on the delivery side we
can do something that is unique right
because we can for instance maintain the
current application deliver just a
subset of the functionality of this new
architecture without impacting the user
so potentially we can say 30% of our
users are receiving the discovery in
playback microphone 10 instead of the
previous application that is a single
page application but at the same time I
can reuse all the rest for maintaining
the other note the authentication
landing page stuff like that so it's a
lot this architecture allows us to
deploy wherever we want when we want in
a specific country and is gradually the
the new the new
version of a malcontent like we can do
with microservices if you think about I
don't know Bluegreen deployment or
Canada releases we can do exactly the
same thing with this architecture so if
we think about this what we have we have
gained with with a microphone and so
first of all and foremost microphone 10
is not a component is a representation
of a sub-domain
that is matching exactly the structure
of our organization its technology and
framework agnostic as I said where I can
develop a one microphone tending one
technology and use another one for
another microphone then each microphone
tend expose a lifecycle method that is
used by the bootstrap when we want to
unload the micro front end or mount
amount from tenon doing some things
inside that each team inside the
microphone can can share components code
style any other stuff like that but they
cannot do that outside the microphone
tent because that is going to slow down
everything I work in a lot of large
organization managing hundreds of
developers and when you start to
abstract and have a team that is
centralizing code is where the
throughput is a going nuts because we
you start to have a centralized version
of your code and every time if you need
to change you need to do a number and
additional abstraction the code became
more difficult to maintain and the
six-month time the throughput is gone we
studied this way we can isolate the team
that can pick the data can take their
own decision and they can innovate
inside that the other interesting thing
with this we can test different building
systems one microphone 10 could be brick
there could be let's say build with I
don't know web pack or another one with
parcel and and so on so we can really
have a less a granularity of choice that
we can do with as this is brilliant so
what we achieve so first of all that is
for me pretty interesting we were able
to to onboard
five teams unless in a couple of weeks
time so after the first week they were
able immediately to contribute the
codebase because they are completely
independent they don't have to wait for
understand deeply the architecture they
have like their own single page
application that is really tiny and
small the domain is more they can
understand the domain deeply and then
they can they can go and I start to work
on that
we have currently over a hundred of
developers that are working on the same
code base that is brilliant because I
also in a distributed way because we
have people in in Poland we have people
in London and we are we are opening
right now and you dev Center in after
them and and that is one of the power of
this finally that the developers have
the freedom as possibility to innovate
and owning the code end-to-end and not
just part of that because often too
often architects are thinking just on
the API layer but it's not the API layer
that is that the complex one because
currently we have a lot of let's say way
and and patterns and architecture that
could help us to to scale it up but
forefront and we don't have much so if
you want to start to look deeply on
microphone dance I pick these two
products there aren't many as I've seen
as I've showed before you can have like
an open components there are other ways
to do that like Taylor which is but the
two things that for me are closer to my
mind's that are are these two framework
one is single SBA that is not well known
but is providing a structure that is
very similar to what we are built
unfortunately discover that too late in
the process process like a year or a
year after that we started to work on
this but it is a really interesting one
and then flimsy as fringes provides a
slightly more flexibility and then
freedom we compared to single SBA but is
still another interesting one is
leveraging reactive programming behind
the scene and you can create components
with different with different frameworks
and the fringe is will let's say collect
them and show them inside their ask a
folder so this is an interesting one as
well in order to wrap up I would like to
just summarize what we have seen till
now so when we scale from 10 application
the problem is not scaling
infrastructure is scaling the teams and
we have to take in consideration this
because it's very very important to have
the right fruit put to reduce the
communication of rather between teams
last but not least often developers are
moving from one company to another one
and I don't know how is the the the
industry here but in London they they
are changing more or less every year
year and a half
mainly because they want to try
something new but we microphone talents
you are basically providing them what
they are looking for inside the
organization and also it could be a good
way to retain people last but not least
I'm working right now on if you're
interested to know more about microphone
tents obviously because in 30 minutes
it's very difficult to summarize
everything I'm writing right now a
report for a Riley that would be a free
report probably will be available by the
end of the year I'm doing some a
learning session one will be the 18 of
October online that is fully free you
can check out my social profile and
hopefully from a next year I will be
able to dedicate some of my time on
writing a full book on on microphone
tense that's it for me I know that we
have some time for for questions but if
we are not able to speak right now and
question anything I'm around for their
own two days so please feel free to stop
me and challenge all the ideas that they
share because as I said at the beginning
is two years work and we are we are
going to the past and having a fresh
point of view it could only out thank
you very much
[Applause]