welcome everyone in this short
screencast I'm gonna show you about a
sink weight which recently made its way
to the new version of JavaScript all the
code that I'm gonna be running works
perfectly on Chrome but you have to make
sure to run this using a transpiler like
bubble in order to have full browser
support so let's get started the example
that I'm gonna take today is assuming
you're gonna make a function for our API
and this function for our API expects
URL and we want to be able to use it by
doing API for example the users and then
logging this to the console so let's get
started I'm gonna make an async function
so I'm gonna have an async function here
which allows me to use the await keyword
inside and I'm gonna use fetch if you
haven't if you don't know about fetch
make sure to watch my previous video and
then I'm gonna define like a base URL so
I'm gonna say this is the base URL for
my API and I'm gonna take the same
example which is Jason placeholder but
of course without the users so that's
the base URL and I'm gonna fetch base
URL + URL or the endpoint that was
passed here and no because of because of
async await I could basically do Const
response equals a weight fetch so rather
than having a chaining the rather than
resolving the promise here by having
then than two response etc you can
actually use a weight and then extract
the response here so this basically you
can think about it wait for the response
until it completes and then extracted
here and then once again we need because
we need to convert it to JSON I can do
cons data equals a weight response dot
JSON and now I can simply return data
and let me show you how cool is that you
can now use API users and then you can
basically simply do just console.log
yes let's run it in the browser and and
yeah it works so here's how you could
also work it I can request the list of
posts and
I can also do console.log and it works
if you are confused a little bit about
the syntax that's basically because you
can basically do it like this so this
will give impact the response or the
data and then I'm gonna pass it back
because to console.log delete data but
since I'm calling this console log
function with the same arguments are
basically zip it all the way down to
just console clock so that's it for
today make sure to subscribe and I'll be
releasing a lot of new videos soon thank
you
[Music]