dear friends and followers and the short
screencast I'm going to show you a new
feature in chrome dev tools that will
help you analyze the amount of
JavaScript and CSS that you're shipping
and especially on mobile where
everything in performance especially
critical so let's get started I'm going
to go to chrome dev tools and then I can
hit command shift P and then click on
coverage so this is the new coverage
feature in chrome dev tools then I can
start instrument coverage and then I can
go for example to Google flights you
will see in real time the JavaScript
resources and CSS resources that are
being requested and at the same time you
can see how much of this javascript is
being used in green and how much of it
is not being used in bread so 1.7
kilobyte of JavaScript 41% of it is not
being used that's approximately I think
it's okay for this kind of website but
this is still running in real time and
you have to use the websites more
because the more you use it the more of
your javascript is being used and that
makes a lot of sense so after you use
this website maybe you use most of the
functionalities you can then click on
the JavaScript and if I make this
smaller you can see the lines here green
show these are the lines that are being
used whereas those that are red are not
being used and I think in the case of
Google Sites it's very well optimized
for mobile but if I go to assert it to a
different website so if I stop and clear
go to Trello calm which is probably not
very well optimized for mobile when I
start recording you can see the entire
jQuery library is being loaded but we're
barely using about 35% of it so 65% of
it is not being used so you see we're
wasting a lot of resources to load
JavaScript and CSS that we will not use
so if I double click on it here and
let's go again scroll down
and you will see big chunks of unused
jQuery code or unused JavaScript codes
so make sure to use this tool whenever
your shipping fast experiences
especially on mobile as it'll help as it
will help you rule out all the
JavaScript and CSS that you will not
need I hope you enjoyed this tip and see
you soon
[Music]