hey everyone in this video I'm gonna
talk to you about dynamic imports I'm
gonna show you a specific use case where
I've used dynamic imports on learn
JavaScript online on all lessons I want
to display a thumbs-up and thumbs-down
preview over here and then when you
click on it it opens an optional
feedback where you can send it so this
is both for negative reviews and also
positive reviews this is some
functionality that I'm not going to use
on every single page because if I go
back I will have the editor and I'll
have the challenge page and in a
challenge page I have the editor and
completely different functionality so
that's why it doesn't make sense to
always include this JavaScript section
that is responsible for the feedbacks
because then as I add more features to
this website the mores can become slower
and I definitely don't want it to become
slow so let's take a look at the code
here this is the code for the lesson
review it's not very fancy and it could
be much much better I'm not using any
framework over here so I just have a
string of the element that I'm
displaying and I've got a bunch of code
that actually makes it work and what I
do is that in the lesson so whenever I
know that this is a lesson I want to
dynamically import it so I want to only
import it when I know I will definitely
need it and rather than doing it as an
import at the top like this where you do
an import and then I don't have anything
exported from this module so I just
import the lesson reviewed ojs rather
than doing that and including the script
as a burden for every single page on my
website I will instead dynamically
import it and here's the syntax for it
it's simply an import using the
parentheses and this makes it a dynamic
import which you can call from anywhere
inside your code so you can even call it
inside an event listener or a fetch
callback and then you get the path to it
that's gonna be lesson review Dulce s
and this returns a promise so you can
resolve it and do something when it's
fulfilled and if you're exporting stuff
you can also access it under the module
if it was a default function then you
call it with module the default if it
was
action or if it was something else like
other method you can call it like this
but I'm not exporting anything so optic
I'll get rid of all of this and let's
take a look at browser support so
dynamic imports work on the following
browsers Firefox has it behind the flag
in the developer edition but you can
already use it because when you're using
webpack webpack makes sure that the
dynamic imports will work in all
browsers so that's pretty much it but if
you keep it as is once you build your
project you're going to get a zero ojs
or one dodgy s you will get the bundle
ID so instead you have to tell what Park
what's the name of this chunk you do
that with the web pack chunk named
comment so this is a special comment
that's read by a buck and then I'm gonna
say this is gonna be lesson review now
let's take a look at this if I go in the
browser this is the web version because
this is what I already did and I reload
the page and because we are on the
lesson page you will see over here that
I have the lesson review being loaded so
this is the dynamic import being loaded
so it only renders on pages where it's
needed which means if I go back I will
not find this lesson review anywhere in
this page just like any other
performance tip it doesn't mean all of
your inputs should be dynamic inputs
because that might slow things down you
have to measure and see if it has any
impact another thing you can do which
I've also been doing in this website in
some places but it requires a polyfill
to work on all browsers is to use the
request idle callback and then if you've
got a lot of work that you need to do
you can just delay this until the
browser has some idle time but don't
forget that you need a polyfill for that
at the time of recording so when used
properly dynamic imports can help you
ship and experience as fast as possible
and then dynamically import or lazy load
other functionality that you may not
need immediately and this also helps you
add more and more features without
really slowing down your web application
if you only import the ones that you
need I hope you enjoyed this quick tip
and I'll see