so good evening thanks for remaining
that's that's great as a good
achievement for me so tonight I would
like to to share my experience because
the reason that let's say like in
microservices a lot of literature
literature and a lot of information how
to deal with microphone tense and
therefore what I'm trying to do is I
mean this mission to share as much as
possible what we are doing why we take
we took a certain path in our company
and and so forth
okay so Who am I my name is Luca I'm a
VP of architecture at the zone I'm a
Google developer expert and running the
loaded on the JavaScript community so
let's start from the beginning okay I
think many of you or at least this is my
experience started with in a startup or
a new project greenfield project to work
on something with the hard deadline or
you need deliver as fast as you can so
in our case we had like roughly the
beginning seven people to aggregate six
different companies that were and
developing not only the backend layer
but also the front-end layer that was a
single page application a big classic
and it has to work there is a nice
requirement has to work not only on web
and mobile but also on around 14
different TV devices so set the boxes
console web mobile all that and that is
for me where we're usually developers
shines because there are a lot of
strings and we're not used anymore
because we have this amazing quad-core
the computers that are rendering
everything instead on TVs is pretty
funny so on the back end what we have
done is creating object model it we
decided to have just moon would be for
the back end and we wear like roughly
internally not many people we work with
some for parties it was a an interesting
journey and then we launched the the
service that I will tell you in a moment
what it is and suddenly we start using
to have success and it was like a very
nice feeling
the problem was there was a month after
the release so we didn't expect that
much success and obviously a lot of us
we're thinking okay well so now what do
we do because we started to see some
challenges how to scale the part we
started to use we use AWS for we're an
AWS shop so we are using heavily that
part and it was pretty nice so I
convinced the the pistas to do an
investment and work with micro services
because obviously there is a way we can
scale the company there is a way that we
can they've identified the bonded
context around our our domain we can
start to work with domain driven design
we start to identify what are let's say
the best practices definitely there is
some overhead but overall if you want to
scale a business that a solution that
was pallet the reality though is what do
you do own from them and that was a
question that I had in my career several
times because at that stage you know it
was pretty obvious that at some point we
were scaling but scaling like
blitzscaling
and it's it's not an easy thing because
on front-end usually you don't speak
much about architecture usually you
steal the wisdom from from the past so
you look at I don't know MV IDC I you
look from different type of
architectures but in reality no one is
talking about scale because now is
becoming more complex that system so can
we do something that was my question at
the beginning so I think we can it's not
perfect but it's it's a trade of name 40
usually says that the reason to the
perfect architecture there are only the
last worst one and I fully agree with
this because in reality is always a
trade off is based on the context where
you operate is based on the skills of
your people is based on several things
that are outside the technical part and
often we don't take in consideration the
part as architects as ly developer tech
leads this is very important because if
you ignore the company structure you
don't try to change that it could bite
yourself in in a few months and that
that was a huge problem so what we came
about was this architecture that was the
beginning and now we move to this so
what we started to do is
okay so let's think about what are the
principle of micro-services so we would
like to have independent releases we
would like to have decisions that are
made domain by the main pieces the main
business domain I don't want to have any
more attack lead that is imposing the
decision at first is the beginner
project and for the next foreseeable
future maintaining the same the same
thing that is something that honestly
when I was a developer and the tech lead
I didn't like much but I do understand
why I was like that and the investment
for the company wasn't always there
because obviously if you ask to the
company I need to write an application
that is I don't know 10 years old it
takes a lot of effort a lot of
development and you cannot really do
that but with that potentially we can do
that potentially we can start to do what
we are used to do on on the micro
services so applying strangle pattern on
the old application and that's more or
less what we have done and that will
guide you to the journey one piece that
is very important for me is the routing
part so one thing that we need to nail
almost upfront is how do you route
between microphone tents and there are
several ways I will I will show you what
we are doing on our side but as I wrote
here you can you can do that on the edge
you can do on server side you can do
client side there are plenty of
possibilities so let's try to define
what is a microphone tense because there
are many information out there so for me
microphone 10 is the representation of a
business subdomain and that is very
important so we start from from domain
driven design they allow independent
implementation with same or different
technology finally they should avoid
should avoid sharing logic I know that
is very controversial controversial
because we learn something different
abstraction and that fix but it's not
always the case and finally are owned by
a single team so those for me are the
key characteristics that are important
for 4 micron deaths because having those
characteristics allows you to work
independently to take local decision
over global decision and obviously yes
there are let's say some coordination
between teams there are community of
practices there are several things that
are happening outside your team but the
reality is no one better than you that
you're working that domain can take a
decision
than anyone else because in reality
certain decision you shouldn't get just
a one decision that fit them all you
need to find the right decision for your
business MA and that's why we work with
that the other thing is scaling on front
m is not a technical problem it's a
social problem because the reality think
about that if you produce past material
time some static files you have to see
the end that is absorbing that the heat
but the reality is when you are scaling
the person for the people factor human
being factor is very very important way
more important infrastructure for us
princess our infrastructure for front
end is pretty basic so we have like a
cloud form distribution we have an s3
bucket and we store everything there and
we have a lambda the edge in front and
we see later on the Y but the reality is
is the how I can have in our case a lot
of their centers and work with all those
people and accordingly and not blocking
each of them because the communication
over ad is always a pain if you remember
of if you are a developer I remember
when I was a developer having external
dependencies
it was super frustrating and I struggled
to who to finish my sprint every time
because you really need to nail the part
you need to wait for another team and
maybe obviously for that team is not a
priority that what what you're asking
for and so on and so forth
so we would like to have like a speed of
delivery we would like to have an
implement an independent permutation and
and that we want we would try to avoid
sharing logic that is something that
will come back later so there are
several there are several companies that
are embracing microphone plans it's not
just us and there are way more than that
New Relic is another one we will talk
about observability so it's good to
mention that each of them have their own
way to implement that now in this talk I
would like to cover what we have done
because obviously is the part that can
go deeper and share the challenges and
everything but I'm writing a lot around
the different microphone dense
architecture so feel free to check on on
my Twitter account my my updates so here
what we have is I will skip for a moment
but let's think about the open table
open table is a very interesting use
case here in London that was the DX team
that created what they call open
component that is a framework that
allows you to compose on the fly your
microphone dance at the server level and
serve and basically serve them like a
normal page at the CDN level so you
basically heat the city and absorb all
the traffic and what they do is they
have a registry like a docker registry
or NPM with all the micro front-ends and
everyone can from any different location
they have a fair amount of wealth
freedom centers one in Australia one in
San Francisco and one in London but I
could be wrong and they are if there is
a component that is interesting for you
or if there is a part of the application
that could be oh so more complex than
just the component it could be like I
don't know something that isn't present
in the page this prominent is at the
page you can you can take that from from
the library and then merge everything
and then you can ship it it's pretty
pretty powerful they created they made a
lot of investment around the developer
experience CLI and they let's say
developer experience in general the the
the CI the CD and so on and that was one
thing and as far as they know who sees a
we have a sky scanner here I know that
is also embraced by sky scanner yes it's
confirmed so well not with the nice face
but it's nice interest rate interface
framework is another one that salons
random was one of the first that I saw
not talking about microphone tanks but
I'm embracing that the logic at the
beginning they had what they call is
called Taylor GS and basically they do
also for them these let's say fact that
they assemble the microphone dance on
the server side and then they are serve
with them obviously they have a
different challenge because they have
personalization and other things that
they cannot be cached
but recently they move away from that
pattern because they were assembling a
HTML fragment and now they decided to go
last purest and they decide to go with
react and they create a library of react
component graph QL and basically there
is an API
is describing how to compose the the
page and they serve through decision
again I know another another way to
manage that then there is exciting clued
that is running on on the edge so CDN
and the interesting part there is a
language that is was let's say they
tried to be a standard with w3c and and
it was proposed by Akamai so currently
the main issue that you have with the
outside included is the fact that not
all the city ends are using that and
therefore if you if you try to have a
multi skin a multi CDN strategy or you
want to migrate from one city and to
another one you need to pay attention
that you don't that you have all the
function either you are looking for so
it's another interesting one finally
Spotify so if I had is using iframes I
know that probably many of you are
laughing but for the desktop application
so they move away from that
implementation on the web because it was
definitely not optimized at all but if
you check inside your desktop
application I like to decompose things
so you can see that they created some
spae files that are basically zip file
or renaming as s.p.a and inside there
you have like HTML page with JavaScript
and the bundled and CSS that's a very
simple web works and is also used by
ASAP they release a framework or widget
framework that does basically they
compose that thing but if you think
about that before you laugh again 4sp
makes a lot of sense because they are in
control which browser the user can use
produces b2b platform so they can really
say listen you know what this one is
going to work XYZ so as you can see
there are there are several thing so
let's see the what we have done so first
of all how many of you knows the zone ok
feel them so currently imagine this
platform that is an OTT platform similar
to Netflix but for sports and we do
mainly live sports with 9 in currently
in nine countries on roughly 30
different devices nowadays and it's
interesting because obviously you have
all the problems of scalability you have
all the problems of the Champions League
final is starting so a millions of users
joining the platform happy days
the reality is also very interesting
from the human part so how do you scale
300 engineers all over the all over the
Europe so at the beginning I remember I
was the second person that was the joy
in the zone in the tech side because the
at beginning they were using third-party
companies and they that was the the city
was talking with me I said listen every
time that you design something please
take in consideration also the human
part is not just the technology part
because it definitely is important but
we are going to have hundreds of people
and now you can imagine how much I was
laughing when I was the second one and
it was looking to the guy close to me
that was the first so it was pretty
interesting so what we have done we
started to have let's say quite a few
teams so fast forward a few years from
2016 now we are from 50 that we started
we are roughly 3,000 and all over the
world not only on tech obviously but
that is how we let's say divide the our
our strategy and as you can see there
are tons of teams and here there are
missing some obviously I try to get
let's say the most prominent one but
sometimes our cross-functional teams
sometimes are not because the problem is
if you have a cross-functional team and
you are designing API with one platform
or the other platform start to complain
so you need to abstract that part and
say ok so politic wise we need to define
an API that is so we have a team that is
just to be beckoned and team the
multiple teams that we front-end and
consume in the API it depends from the
complexity of the domain but there are
some things like for instance the sports
data team that is doing an to end
everything so when you see something on
on top of the video player that is the
sports data team that create a component
on the UI that is ingesting some
real-time data and this show being
inside the straw bar of the video player
or other parts of the video so it is
very and I think that is also one of our
strengths we didn't at the beginning we
were very fragmented we didn't think ok
so now we have like a bit of I don't
know authentication and authorization in
London and the beta in in Amsterdam and
then we
a bit of TVs in London and another bit
we have in Katowice in Poland
I was painful at the beginning and when
I thought okay now we are going to scale
but we're going to scale hard so we
ramped up like a tough centre in
Amsterdam from 0 to 140 people in the
month it could be a problem because
again it's a social problem is more than
tactical problem so what I did at the
time I stopped everyone including CTO
and they said listen I think here we are
doing something wrong because we are
designing our architecture based on our
teams where they are located my reality
what we should do is the other thing so
the other way around because if you know
the combo is low that is basically
stating that you design your
architecture based on on the company
structure you have the inverse caucus
maneuver that is doing the opposite so
you create the architecture and you
structure your team based on the on the
architecture and this is exactly what we
have done and so far is is a pretty good
success that will show you later on a
few other hints on on the round that ok
so what we have done as you have seen in
the previous slide we have created
something that's called the bootstrap
that is not the framework just as free
or not nothing to do with that ok so
absolutely nothing it was just because
it's the first thing that you load and
what we identify look at data looking
talking with our domain expert and
trying to understand how to split this
monolith was understanding the user
journey understanding how the user were
consuming our platform and then suddenly
we discover that we have like quite a
lot of people that were going to landing
pages and then there was a drop of
people were going to authentication they
arrived to the payment they didn't like
the payment methods that were there and
then they never finalized the sign up
the other thing that we notice is when a
user is signed up they will never logout
they always remain there so all the code
related on the authentication the SDK
for credit card all the other things are
not useful you wind unload at the moment
but at at the time but it wasn't useful
at all so we know that we we had to
figure out something so what we did is
ok so we can
lies our applications vertically so we
can start to say okay we have like a
landing page proxy that is loading
landing page because we have roughly
hundreds of landing page that are
dependent from country depends from the
device depends from the campaign and so
on so we need something that is
orchestrating a bit then we need an
authentication bit that contains signing
sign up that contains the retrieve email
password then we have another part that
is the core part for the zone is the
discovery part so I want a catalog I
want to the best video player for life
possible I won't watch my content at any
time I want to watch in any device now
we have the customer support part and
finally we have my account those are the
things that we saw we bucket eyes let's
say our user journey and we found those
as prominent microphone tents so we
decided to go with this so we decided to
take our application split it but there
was a missing thing how do we move from
landing pages to authentication
that was the big question okay so we
came up with this idea of bootstrap that
basically what it does is a a nutshell
ok so it's like a container that is the
first Finity load and it will always be
there for you the moment that you type
the zone.com or you go to add to the
application it's always there we will
see later on what it does but at the
moment the key thing is that the
bootstrap is orchestrating this
microphone dance and is the one that is
loading or unloading the landing page
and move to authentication or vice versa
so we we created some routes so the
first thing is each microphone then has
to represent a subdomain matching the
business structure so currently what we
have done is we already have the product
eminent was almost let's say dividing in
the way that we divided them the
application but we force certain things
and currently is working very well
because they have their dedicated team
depends from the device but they all
speak the same o pictus language that
was the goal then we wanted to have
technology framework agnostic microphone
that and I know that a lot of people say
ok about do you share some some
libraries do you if they share component
stuff like that
so at the beginning we were very very
pleased no we didn't share anything so
you have like because of what we have
seen so for landing page we just have
and react with a static HTML because we
compile that sorry we render at compile
time and we serve static page for
authentication we have a single page
application that was made with direct
but the reality is when you are in
you're in as we saw before so therefore
when you load the the main thing the
core domain of the zone you just load
once and that's it also on TV the
performances are improving so we move
from in certain device from a startup of
the application of 40 seconds to in very
old devices to less than 20 so those
kind of things discuss of logic we're
not only dedicated for web but also
because for us is very important TVs and
we want to provide the possibility to
pick your technology so there was an
interesting use case landing page guys
that they saw their rack books and they
wanted to try the trying production
didn't say anyone to anyone this thing
was working no problem at all
it was pretty simple pretty quick in one
sprint they replaced what they wanted to
to test the pudding production was
working hit by minutes of user done and
then they share their let's say
information they shared what they have
learned from that that was pretty
interesting use case then the other
thing is I want to have a microphone on
these autonomous I don't want to deploy
them the authentication mic from time
coordinating that with the discovery I
want that they can deploy just one of
that because that's the whole point
if I can do that and they need to make
some some say strong decisions therefore
no code sorry no obstructions as poor as
much as possible I can I can do that
then inside the microphone thank the
team can share components code size and
so on that is another thing that we we
we assess we create independent building
system now I know that a lot of people
would think ok but why you don't provide
that we provide the basics so we have
like a drone that is running but what is
inside a container that is running on
drone is up to the team to the size
because they can have optimization that
other teams shouldn't shouldn't have or
they want to translate certain things
that don't have so they have like
several plugins for roll-up and flora
for web puck and they can use them share
between teams it's not a problem at all
but that's that's how it works you have
an important thing for me is when you
have a booster uploaded you always load
one Mike from 10 per time you will never
compose anything on the client side you
always load a single page application or
a single page because in that case it
means that you're using the they let's
say the Holy Trinity of JavaScript so
use HTML uses as huge JavaScript and you
don't have to compose an if you don't
have to remember with if you if there is
a new tool that you wanted to use you
will be able to and you can also split
wewe happen at some point it happens at
some time that the complexity of a
domain became too big on the back on the
front end so we started to split the
domain in moving too much 1/10 and now
is this working like a charm so as I
said the microphone tent for us is the
Holy Trinity of fronting an index.html a
JavaScript file for the application a
vendor JavaScript that has a high TTL on
oncidium and the stasi SS or wherever
the team decide whether that is how we
work so when you type the zoom comm what
happens is that you load the bootstrap
and immediately and is the the part that
is doing the logic and what is
responsible for is doing an application
startup that is basically a set of
course to understand if you are
authenticated not only authenticated in
which country you are and other settings
like feature toggles and so on it's
abstracting input up to operation
therefore web storage and I know that
you say it but it's a pretty standard
yes unfortunately not on all the TVs so
instead of having microphone tanks then
knows about it's single TV that they are
running I can have
agnostic microphone tans that are
running in any device potentially
depends from the performance is
obviously and and bootstrap is taking
hear about the abstraction layer so you
just expose an API to say save save or
get so that is routing between
microphone tanks that we saw before and
it's sharing configuration across modem
microphone dance so imagine that I'm not
only ticketed I go to the authentication
microphone that
perform let's say the signing and I
receive a token and then I pass that to
the booster up the booster store on the
local storage and the next microphone 10
that is loaded will can will retrieve
that the J double D token from the from
the bootstrap and validate if you still
valid
they still valid we will go ahead and
show otherwise we kick out the user to
another page now what is the booster op
in reality it's just a JavaScript file
vanilla JavaScript nothing crazy and
very light it's loaded at the beginning
is always there and expose a set of
api's that are used for a microphone
tense for sort of thing could be life
cycle it could be lets say in
communication for i/o and operation so
imagine that for instance one question
usually have these stages or how about
how do you load them the microphone pan
and so we thought what is the most basic
way to load some HTML you can use the
URL yeah but we need we should need to
replicate all the logic of each single
microphone tan or HTML in reality is XML
so we can parse it so let's parse it
so we basically talk in the HTML that
are the tags that we are interested and
the bootstrap is loading and what it
does is appending inside itself the
different elements that's what it does
the interesting bit of this this there
are several frameworks out there that
are starting as a starting point of a
microphone and this is just JavaScript
but there is a strong reason why we pick
this because we care to provide an
immediate feedback to the user so what
we can do here and certain micron Dells
are doing are compiling at runtime a
skeleton that is served immediately the
moment that we download the HTML the
user has immediate feedback and then
they start to load in background all the
JavaScript all the other stuff and that
is working on TV as well as web so ok so
as I said the boost exposes some methods
the lifecycle methods so it's not final
microphone then when
is finished to load and when he's
finished to when it is about to unload
and we can use that for cleaning out the
pointers so in that case the interesting
bit we did there is we take the keys of
in the bootstrap we take the keys of
what we have at the beginning of the
application because we loaded just the
booze drug and every time that Theresa
Macken from 10 this is a pending inside
the bootstrap we retrieve we scan or the
the Dom nodes and JavaScript inside the
window and we take like just the keys
inside the memory and then when we
unload the macro from 10 we just remove
all the things so it's always clean
obviously there is for a moment between
in transition between my two front ends
there is a moment where there is a bit
of let's say memory overlap but usually
it doesn't hurt and not it doesn't hurt
even on TV that usually you have like
strong goes through your memory and then
you have local storage and another stuff
ok so apart from microphone times we
have also distinction of components so I
said the microphone dance is a business
representation Bob we use components we
have some area of the application that
are really complex video player for us
having and if you're familiar with video
players usually all the open source that
you find a commercial licenses are
mainly focus on beauty but we are a live
company and the eristic soph the video
player for life is completely different
so we had to spin up a team dedicated to
that in order to build our own video
player for all the devices and trust me
it wasn't easy at all because also many
that we are using inference one that I
remember is Shaq player soccer player is
a maintained by Google as openSUSE video
player and we change the eristic of
their or that because it wasn't good
enough so those are the challenge that
we have so that team what it does is
exporting a component like you have like
a components library and these embedded
inside the microphone hands like you
always work you don't have to compose
anything around time you don't have to
reinvent the wheel
you just have a library on NPM and you
just use it simple like that obviously
you need to define the contract first so
we always if we have some parts that are
shared we we gather with the teams and
the architects and we try to figure out
what are they
guys that we need in order to manage the
model there but when we define that they
can work in parallel and it's not a
problem
the other interesting beat that I
decided to add is the cannery release
thing so they caught the company ask me
can we have a way to in general not wait
for building all the microphone pans and
deploy them and there at the beginning
was a bit puzzled because I said yes
more micro-services this is no problem
at home from 10:00 what we have so
because our architecture was very simple
crowd from and that's free I thought ok
let's write lambda the edge now at the
edge if you're not familiar it can be
triggering in four stages when there is
a viewer request
origin request origin response and
viewer response and what it does is you
can add logic on the edge so you don't
hit you say you hit the closest the AWS
death center sorry the data center where
the the request is coming from and in
that case you can orchestrate sort of
things so what we have done basically is
deciding in so we started to say ok we
want to deploy in a specific country on
a specific browser or device and we want
to deploy that and every time there is
another request boom it goes to 1.0 so
that allows us to do many and
incremental deployment per day then
before it was a nightmare in particular
for TV so the other guys thing is we can
we decide to go a very deep granularity
so country and browser because this
depends from the browser what kind of
video player you need to use and that
was pretty interesting because I have
like if search on YouTube there is a
talk that I did that bring vent about
this with a SS I was an interesting
topic we also managed to do SEO through
that so we can redirect the crawler to
specific pages that are dedicated only
for crawlers and surprise surprise we
discover that also Amazon is doing that
with amplify they are doing when you
deploy something on amplified they're
switching the the things to letters was
a pretty pretty nice understanding that
we were on the right track ok so as I
said the dissolve structure on the DDD
part
something like that so we try to take
all out all the things that you have
seen so far and and map our teams in
this way so we define following Vedic or
domain the generic anime and the core
and support enemy and we map our teams
in that our company in this way and that
than what we have done is saying okay
perfect
where is the core team where it's based
but London we have like all the the POS
and all the marketing people so probably
we need to Twitter it fast on this
because this is our core business
generic is Amsterdam so we have all the
payments guys that are managing my
account help onboard in front and
back-end or the partnership and
everything and basically the person that
is far from you is like a couple of a
couple of steps so it's pretty good
because then there is
cross-contamination between Megami
between the center but it was pretty
good course reporting in Katowice
because we have a lot of TVs and we
found a little pretty nice place there
and also for mobile native teams we have
also some back-end stuff but we are
moving to London now we have a global
team is my team DX so developer
experience cloud Engineering's travel
engineers and s eries and though
together basically we are supporting
those things okay so what we achieved so
first of all when we were scaling up one
day I arrived to the office and they
have like five new teams that that join
in in London and in basically they were
working on the same project in influence
the the nice thing was they were capable
after because they have the freedom to
take certain decision and who use the
technology they want they were able to
let's say do in the first print already
provide some some value for the company
and deliver something because the all
the automation was sorted out and they
started to have the first part on the UI
now we have over 300 techies 350 attacks
that are working on the same platform
there are obviously some part that our
back-end some part that our front-end
but
and some part of the coffee some part of
the layer that is heat by by the users
and so forth but it is really difficult
arriving to that in one year and a half
and having those guys that are creating
value for the company not for also for
the scalability issues and the
challenges that we have but also because
those people that's the first time that
they they work together and really
namsun we have 24 different countries
there so there is a huge diversity and
is not easy at all
but we were able to make the work
the other interesting thing with the
risk our releases so it's like two years
that we don't have an s-1 incident we do
multiple release per day I remember at
the beginning we did in the first week
26 release of the video player and we
were literally switching turning on
turning off the different part or so
which browser in which country where we
wanted to test it and we were testing in
real time in production then go back if
you didn't work and then we doubling our
user base every year so at the beginning
you know when you have like few users is
one thing when you start to add millions
and millions starting became more
complex that's it for me I know that you
maybe you have several questions so I
left some time for that
you