here's a quick tip whenever you're
working with grid or flexbox
and you're not entirely sure why
something looks the way it does use
Firefox dev tools which has some amazing
layout dev tools let's take a look so
I'm here running Firefox developer
edition because I need to be on Firefox
65 if you're watching this video in the
future you will have access to these dev
tools as long as you're on Firefox 65
and above I'm over here on this website
grid by example and if you take a look
at this website you can see it the nav
bar over here is using a display flex in
fact you can see that from the dev tools
over here from the inspector panel
because we have this flex icon and now
as a Firefox 65 we can click on this or
you can simply go to the right and you
see this is a Flex container and then
you can toggle this or enable it and
this will show you an overview of this
Flex element alongside its Flex items
that's really useful if you're still
getting started with flex or if you're
not sure why something is behaving the
way it does and you can see here this is
a Flex container and these are the Flex
items over here not only that you can
also see from these boxes over here that
we are using justify content space
between so if you experiment with this
and use space around you will exactly
see where the space is being distributed
same thing if you do Center or flex and
or flexor and we've got the same helpers
for grid so if you scroll down a little
bit and if we take a look at the wrapper
over here we can see that it's using a
grid I can click on the grid and now I
can see the layout of the grid here on
the right and you can also see that on
the screen itself
this is the grid gap and these are the
grid cells you can also put the mouse on
top of them and you will see which grid
cell this is and if you're working with
multiple grids or maybe even massive
grids you can change the colors of this
indicator and that will make it clearer
for you to understand which one of these
grids this one is that's a nice tool
that I really like in Firefox give it a
try and let me know what you think and