[Music]
my name is Kayla furnance and I'm
talking about reactive programming I
come from Brazil and it's my first time
in Italy in Europe indeed and I am
software developer consultant at
ThoughtWorks and I'm also Judy like he's
had the angler and web technologies okay
I was born in a small city in Brazil and
Brazil is a huge country so my stage has
the same size of the entire Italy now I
live it in some Paulo is the big biggest
city in my country I have two cats and
two sisters and oh my parents are so
proud I'm here with you today they have
no idea what I do for a living then they
came for Italy once they were in a
Europe tour and that time knowing my mom
would go to France I asked her to bring
me some macaroons but I didn't said to
her what was so in Brazil we speak
Portuguese and the word pasta is maca
home and we share of Brazil she gave me
a pack of pasta and I said it's not maca
homem its macaron and is even taught me
to give some context when try to
communicate with people let's start
software engineer has a science has
about 60 years old is a young search
field
I look at all the much of
knowledge we accumulated involved
through these years and every day you
are creating new things and as a Vella
pers who handle the problems every
single day and I believe that the reason
people pay us to think about problems
they need to find a solution and that's
the strain in a xxx way we like to do
that
and did you remember when you start to
learn to code for me it was about 16
years ago when I entering this wonderful
world of programming and for me and I
think for the major people when start to
learn to code they are taught to think
in imperative way and it makes sense
since E is the way computers thinking
imagine a problem a computer should
solve it has some inputs following
sequential steps of some conditionals
that may razuna expected output and this
way of thinking carry main concerns
about how to solve a problem and many
times worried with implementation
details and may distract us about the
main concern you should put our tension
what is the expected behavior what is
the key and not too much on how I have
here application accorded in JavaScript
it has a propose to draw some geometric
shapes in calculate their areas the
rules are quite simple I have the space
there called as canvas so when I click
on it a point is draw when three points
exist a parallelogram that included
those points is wrong and after that a
circle with the same center an area of
parallelogram is hundred and I have also
coordinates an area valise in G's box
alongside the canvas and when I move
those points of shapes are updated in a
way of imperative program this could be
common solution so in my canvas class I
have one click method that draws a point
draw a parallelogram
there are circle update coordinates and
update area and in my point class I buy
another event or move that draws a
parallelogram
there are circle update coordinates and
update area at first sight you can see
the placated cold and clear imagine how
could be this map messy
I have background in web development
most of time think the way but angler is
a reactive system router HTTP requests
components interactions behind the
scenes we use rxjs javascript library to
deal with reactivity although when I
started to create angular applications
the imperative mindset followed me and
that's how looks like the chorus start
creating the famous spaghetti code and
you remember the old web sites who had
less than 20 years ago for web histories
like Stone Age nowadays you have such
dynamic applications so interactive with
rich animations that refreshes it
smoothly for the user experience is
amazing but for the one who create those
applications is a challenge and can
become a crazy test
not only crazy but also can become a
hell you have functions which car backs
depends on other functions it's not so
hard to get in car back hell and the
rule is for me when things start to get
crazy it's time to think to use rxjs and
with your activity program you have many
elements to that has that nature
asynchronous nature like events
animations HTTP requests its variables
chains all of them carry valise that
change over time imagine an array but
those values are emitted asynchronously
in the presentation layer it's so clear
to see that all this interactivity is
obvious but the reactive which is not
limited to front-end applications or
JavaScript ecosystem almost all
languages have our rx library for
example rx Java is the key for enabling
server-side concurrency in each Flickr's
API and not only you can find reactive
in the code itself but also can see that
in some architectural solutions for
example cloudy functions which are even
driving surveillance applications and
the challenge is how do you change our
mindset there was educated to think in
an imperative way how do you break these
visual circles with the same old
thinking you get the same old results
our brain has a reticular activation
system it is compared to a filter that's
work for our brain it's make sure your
brain does have to do
more information that Ricky handle does
reticular activation system plays a big
role on the society information you
perceive daily did help to you
curious phenomena when you say for
example I never see our videos anymore
and after that this type of car Sunday
appear in front of you it's not
necessarily mean than a number of yellow
beers increase it in your city or in
your neighborhood another situation
imagine you are at an airport and there
are so much noise people talking Airport
announcements and in the middle of
artists noise your name is announced it
and it's important information for your
brain and that's the reason your brain
puts its intention on it it's not a
music phenomenon it's how our brain
works in the same way when I start to
pushing yourselves into reactive mindset
the reactive mantra take over our
thoughts everything can be a stream I
agree waved is a formation but I don't
vacate it at any cost
since I believe software engineering
history has sure that you don't have a
silver bullet for all the problems in
approach even braces have trade-offs
there you you have to consider a basis
in many variables and talking about Rx
is hard since it's a such formal concept
our X is a library for composing
synchronously even basing programs use
observable collections that is our xt of
data over time and rxjs implements the
the observable observer partner and
observable represents the application
data and the observer reacts where it's
change but the observable is not a date
I self
he's like the wrapping and the
flexibility of Jesus implementation is
that it can have different observers
that listen to anike observable but
react in many ways and talking about
code what is an observable in rxjs it's
just a function and can you want to tell
me what does this code do there's
something there's nothing okay there's
nothing they say you have to connect the
observable end observer you do that
using subscribe metal so to start
execution an observer is just an object
with three callbacks next arrow and
complete the first go back next pass
value to the observe observer sorry and
in this case you have the subscribe
matter we're passing the message hello
Varun you should see finally in console
hello Verona the second callback is a
error there not price arrow to the
observer and different for the next you
can call any time the next method the
pass any time of object the arrow just
finish in my observable so in this case
you should see in the console hello and
never happen and the third alas Quebec
is complete method so I just finish our
observable in this case you should see
in the console hello
don't it's very important to defer two
types of observables hard and code
observables
the code of service which valise I
created inside the observable in this
case in no matter the moment I subscribe
for example the front Manta
I get all the vowels in the case all the
vowels from this array in the other hand
the heart observables there well I
create outside observable so a classical
example our mouth clicks so you just get
those values that happens after you do
the subscription and the power of rxjs
relates on his operators and we've
Daniel can filter transform you can
change those operators and the rule is
observable always return observable I
don't wanna we're about curious
phenomenon about cats no matter its
scientific also no matter how to get
false
they always falls on their feet for me
it's like a tautology to be or not to be
that's the question
oh there's nothing you can do they can
be done nothing you can sing that can't
be sung
don't forget observables always return
observable I brought some operators the
first one is future it's very similar to
the array method remember observable as
array but those values are emitted
synchronously and in this case just B is
emitted the second one is keep a while
nothing happens until some conditional
is expired so in this case unless
validly the entry no valleys in the
mission didn't start so when valleys 3 I
omit the tree and the next sheet 2 and
about the time you have to wait amount
of time to start a mission so it's very
useful in scenarios such as type
had one day user input must be under
control and in this case I'm using the
interval method that emits an itch at
every second and let me use the boss
time just change that the time I have to
wait and with the take operator they get
the two first emission and completing my
observable and next two are do
transformations
the first one is map it just returns to
two times the valley and the last one is
plug is beautiful why you're not
interesting in the whole object in this
case I just wanna then they just want
the name of the person and
observables require memory subscription
check my memory so it's strongly
recommend and when you it's not
necessary to listen the observable
anymore you should also subscribe you
can do that using explicit calling on
subscribe method or use your P return
like taking or taking - dad - dad under
the hood so it's time to writing code so
let me see if you can okay but I can see
there it's not good
sorry I'm just trying to find out how to
do that anyone can help me please I
sorry I just move to them I want to see
there the best cold
yeah yeah - copy
screen lock I believe is a scream
alright yeah here okay okay oh yeah
sorry about that okay
it's good for you too for everybody see
okay for example I have this application
here so I can transform promises into
observables so I create a new problems
here resolve and reject okay I'll call
resolve method I'll put some time here
just wait a little bit and okay okay and
I can't get these problems here and use
them from method I can transform into an
observable so I can subscribe to it and
just show what's coming and console so
let's see okay
resolve it let's see the difference
about hot and cold observables in scales
I will create an observable here observe
oh sorry observable and we using Create
method and I will create like a vowel
inside
here just a random number rendering and
just call next method passing this value
okay
and I would subscribe to this two times
so subscribe okay I'll do that two times
saving okay is that the value is created
inside observable so they are
independent string there are different
values but for example if I move X
outside mob servable so the value it
create outside is a hot observable in
this case what should happen the same
value okay and we've taken two operator
demonstrate some example and I will
declare an interval here using travaux
method passing for example 500
milliseconds and I declare another one
that is my Max and I can use inter and
to use operators I have to use pipe
method inside I put taken to you and
pass these observable max so I will
subscribe to it and just bring it in in
console
zero one and two and taking a 2 also
completes my observable I can check this
in my third callback second I put just
no and the third one I don't have to put
anything here done saving you don't want
you done okay and I have an operator
that is called
even my observable gets an arrow or is
just completed there is finalized in
this case is I'm completing my
observable so just to see how it works I
can put here oops
yeah okay and when you gather here every
you know observable it's done it's
complete it cannot pass novellas using
act method but it can do something for
example I got the car and other
observable here create using grid method
so I'll call next here okay one ok chew
and equate three oh I forgot to
subscribe subscribing
so you just print those valleys okay
okay one can took a tree but if an arrow
happens here what what should you see
just okay one but you can you cannot
continuum it we if it is observable but
you can create and
you observable sometimes it's user for
your application so in this case we use
pipe here and I you use an operator
called catch error so if it's operator
I'm we return and you observe a book
just we're using off method just for
example okay for oh yeah thank you
and now what should happen I turn you
okay well and you observable with valor
204 Anna let's come back for the
presentation now so after all geez
reactive how could you propose a new
solution for the draw shapes problem
remember three points a parallelogram in
a circle and I have chopped eight your
coordinates and area valleys in my
canvas skies in my own click method I
just draw a point so in my point class I
created a new subject that passed the
coordinate ballast to wherever wants to
listen to it and when I move I also do
that so in my parallelogram I listen to
this new observable subject sorry and
I'm just interesting when I have three
coordinates so there's a reason use a
future operator that draws a point so I
created a new subject that pads the area
in the center to the circle there at
least is listen to that subject and draw
the circles and after that emit an extra
event and let's get into some angular
reactivity so imagine you have to
implement a loading component you can
create a loading service that listen to
router events which are observables so I
have the subject to show loading that
pass the valid - when navigation starch
otherwise on navigation
and Pez Valley false so I have a
specific time of subject let's call it
behavior subject in this case this
subject requires initialization because
I want to make sure that the full value
for loading is false
I haven't used the application i
implemented months ago in angular the
page had three sections and each of both
sections consumes different services and
different data bases so I had a layer a
BFF layer the sense to me they unique JS
object the problem we had if some
service were dead I couldn't load my
entire page so to turn the table i
implemented parallel requests using for
Kajin operator and not only i achieve a
more error easily ending system but also
i could get data faster and I
implemented retry feature just allow the
section that failed those example were
about services and how about components
I had to implement a core component and
you know the expected behavior is open
it on click on its header if there is
some another element the item that is
active you have to close it so in my
accordion template I just put in gherkin
directive and the meat and potatoes are
in my Accord item template so I had a
header and a content section and I use
CSS class to bind properties and the
usage is nesting
I called item each mark origin so my
class
McChord ID component class I create I
even Demeter what is unobservable
and when I open my record I think I just
use
a media notification used a meat method
and in my heart and component I
subscribe for those observables to make
sure I close act are active I think and
I especially like this way to do and
subscribe
so I declare a subject and pass into
taking a chill operator and when I
destroy my component I just completely
subject so I don't need to call a
subscriber explicitly and the cherry on
the top is that component I had to
implement is model component that made
like making HTTP requests and load some
context and did you notice I use a lot
of subject in all my implementations but
those example they don't doesn't have
had the possibility to fail is different
for this one it came failure since is a
HTTP request yeah I couldn't do that so
I will show to you what happens I made
an example here without subject yeah so
I heard I just make you an example for
you to know but it was very similar what
I did I have a dangerous service here
I'm just returning observable of string
I did that put in a valor here and I
will increase it this valley for the
second time I'm simulating error
otherwise it's gonna be success so I'm
gonna turn observable pasinetta returnin
a my model component I have like loading
message when them is loading is getting
the data otherwise it show a message the
message is like you coating Lola or
content
era so I had I put property here there
is a subject the way I try to do the
first time and I just subscribe to this
and I'm using finalized you remember
that otherwise no matter if it gets an
arrow or success I want to remove the
loading so in my app component I'm just
using the load in passing the subject as
input property and I'm usages click to
open a modal so in my app component I
have I create the subject here and when
I click to open model I call open from
the model component and get data so I
just put delay to simulate a real it's
trip request that takes a little bit
longer and using tap just to say I
finish you the the request and I'm you
sketch error to call error if something
that wrongs so let's see what happened
first time should load my compton second
time should get an error and the other
time yeah didn't work so so I have to
back to Terry and in this incredible
article for embellish for me to the
master of XJS on the subject of subjects
what he said about people like me there
are always those subjects while this is
helpful for people neutral XJS and in
that capacity totally fine it's not
really the RX way to handle things like
this so I was not being so reactive here
was a fault and do remember the subject
a partner we were having a gang of four
is very similar they therefore
subjecting rxjs and you have
registered observable so a subject has a
stage if something fail getting an arrow
it's closed I can do nothing anymore
that's the reason I get an arrow in my
model first implementation so and
remember what is observable in rxjs
it's just a function and I try again
okay so you might get a serve see I have
the same implementation so the second
times get an error the other time is
going to be success if I motor component
templates is the same thing in my model
component class is almost the same thing
instead now I have an observable and the
method is the same thing that was done
before and my epic component
I have MEP model but now instead of
passing the subject here am i ng on each
method I'm just using per function here
so I I create a new observable and when
get success I just call next and then I
get error I just call error method so
let's see how what's happened first time
loaded content error and content
loaded
so that's it guys thank you so much
[Applause]
you